Hello everybody. I decided to read the
entire ser manual so you don't have to.
And today I'm going to explain you
exactly how the plug-in works. Now, of
course, this plug-in has been around for
over a decade and it still holds up in
the sound design capability as it's my
main synthesizer that I've been using
for all of this
time.
Yo, what the manual is is 350 pages.
I'll have to read that all over again.
[Music]
Yes, everybody. Serum 2 has come out and
it has been a little bit of a surprising
release for me. Of course, I wasn't
expecting it. I was already hearing some
rumors that it would be releasing soon,
but I was unprepared for it releasing
now. And basically, I spent the last 2
days just experimenting with the plug-in
and going over everything. not just all
of the new stuff that has been added,
which has been wonderful to experiment
with, but also brushing up by reading
through the entire manual, which I
actually did for Serum 2 as well, and
just trying to find every single feature
out there, which I'm able to show in
this video, because I want this video to
be a complete overview of Serum's
capabilities. So, the new interface is
gorgeous. As you can see, it's also a
very colorful upgrade, especially if I
turn on some of the extra things over
here. You can see it's shining. And
overall, I think it's a nice visual
upgrade as well. It just looks a little
bit sharper. It looks a little bit more
pleasing. And in terms of its layout, it
is pretty self-explanatory. Of course,
if you're already familiar with Serum,
then this is going to be very easy to
adapt for you because in overall
interface layout and that kind of stuff
and where you're going to find certain
features, it has stayed completely the
same. But of course, I'm going to assume
that you're completely new with using
Serum and I'm going to go over every
single thing. So, starting off with the
general interface, I'm just going to
start with the top left where you're
going to find the Serum 2 logo. This is
where you can click to resize the
interface if you want it to be bigger or
smaller. Also, if I play a note, I can
go over here and then from here, drag
into an audio
track. So, that will render out an audio
file of whatever you play. Right next to
the serum logo, you're going to have
your main navigation menu. Here, you
switch between the different tabs. On
the top part of the plugin here, we have
our preset browsing area as well as
preset information like the author and
the description. Of course, over here
you can save presets and you have arrows
to go between them. We also have a
button to open up the full preset
browser. Going to go over the feature
set of the preset browser later on in
this video. Then in the corner here, we
also have the main menu. Again, I'm
going to go over some of these options
later on in the video. Below the preset
browser and menu, we have undo and redo
buttons. And then we have a main volume
as well as output monitoring. That then
on the main page brings us to our main
oscillators as well as filters. Of
course, it is going to depend on the tab
what is actually being displayed on the
top page. So here we have the mixer.
Here we have the effect section. We have
the modulation matrix and we have global
settings. The lower part of the
interface is where your modulators are
going to live as well as some other
settings. You can think of the lowest
portion of Serum really as all of the
information needed to actually generate
the notes that are going to be played by
the oscillators and then go through the
rest of the synth. And also over here
there are some extra windows that when
you click on them open up into new
features like the clip and the arp here
for example. So that's going to be the
main interface of Serum. Thank you for
watching. Bye-bye. No, just kidding.
We're going to dive deeper into that. Of
course, let's actually dive deeper into
the oscillators. But before we do that,
I do quickly want to say that when I
said that it took me 2 days to actually
script this video, I wasn't really
joking. So, I would really appreciate it
if you like the video and subscribed and
maybe write an interesting comment down
below to support me in the algorithm.
Also, if you're considering supporting
me financially, there's two ways to do
that. You can a become a channel member
or you can become a Patreon of mine.
Both of course will get you extra
benefits like priority and feedback
streams as well as discounts on my
products. So thank you for doing that.
Now let's get back into the oscillators
of Serum. So Serum now comes with five
different oscillator types. You can
select them from here. We can see we
have a wave table, multisample sampler,
a granular oscillator, and a spectral
oscillator. Right next to the type
selection, you can turn the oscillators
off and back on again. And then to the
right, you can select which of the two
filters they go into. So you can click
over here. There will be a little popup.
You can switch which filter it goes to.
You can set to a mix in between or you
can set to one or entireity to two. As
you can see that is also reflected in
here. So even if this window is closed,
you can still at a glance see what is
happening. You may have also noticed
these buses over here. This is also
where you can send to buses. These buses
are going to be part of the effects
change. So we're going to take a look at
that later. For now though, one of the
things that you need to know about the
wavetables is that they all technically
take samples. This first wavetable
oscillator is going to take a very
specific format of samples which are
going to be the actual wave tables. In
essence, the files that are loaded over
here are just wave files where every
cycle of the wave table is stored in 248
samples and you can have a maximum of
256 different frames. And all of the
different files that you're selecting
over here are nothing more than wave
files in that particular format. And the
interesting thing about this is once you
know the format, you can actually write
code to make wavetables in that format.
That is for example how I made the
wavetables in my base tables pack. But
as I said over here you can select the
different wave tables that you want to
use. For now, as you can see, I only
have the factory wavetables loaded. I
still have to port my factory from serum
one into serum 2. If you don't want to
go through the menu every time though
and select different wavetables like
that. Another way that you can do it is
by these arrows over here where you can,
as you can see, just move back and
forth. Below the wavetable selection
area, we have pitch control. There's
four different pitch controls over here
which is actually very useful because
you have this continuous pitch control
here. As you can see this is just in
decimal numbers. So this is very nice
for modulations. And then we have fine
tuning over here semmitones and then
whole octaves. So depending on what you
need to do with your modulations you can
apply it to different parts. And of
course one of the nice ways is that you
can also set oscillators down and up by
an entire octave as well which is a very
common thing to do in sound design.
Right below our pitch controls, we have
the main waveform display which can be
set to 2D mode or 3D mode. And as you
can see in 3D mode, a line is drawn
which shows where the wavetable position
is selected which is going to be the
actual output of the wave table. And
again, as you can see, if I move through
this, the wave table is actually going
to update. If you want to know the exact
number of the frame that you're playing,
that is displayed over here. And next to
that, we have the phase information. So
we have the actual phase that you can
set here. And then we have phase
randomization. If you edit any of these
parameters, what you'll see is that it
is actually represented in the waveform
what is happening. So with no
randomization, the phase is always going
to start in the same position. And with
this, we can actually change that
position all the way back and forth.
Now, when it comes to serum, a lot of
the information is hidden behind
right-click menus, so-called context
menus. And if I right click on the face,
you can see that we have two options
over here, which are actually specific
to this parameter. These other options
are actually shared among most of the
parameters. So, I'm going to go over
them later when I talk about the
modulation. Now, unfortunately, we
already run into the first option that I
couldn't find the description for in the
manual. And this is one that's even
through testing, I didn't quite know
what it was doing. So, if you know what
rap phase does, please explain it to me
in the comments down below. The other
one though has to do with how notes are
triggered in legato mode in regards to
the phase. So, whether or not you want
the phase to reset on legato notes,
which are notes that are played when
another note is already playing. Now,
users of version one of Serum may
remember that the phase knob also had a
memory position. When you set it all the
way up, it would remember the face of
the last note that you triggered.
There's now actually two options and
they're available over here. We are now
in all voices mode, which is just normal
phase behavior in that it just relies on
these parameters. Over here, we have the
continuous, which is what memory used to
be in serum, where every note takes the
face of where the last playing note
ended and just continues from there. And
then we have the per voice setting which
you need to activate when a note is
playing because then it will take that
note and it will apply the phase of that
note and apply to all future notes that
are played. The final thing that is in
the top area of the oscillator is going
to be the wavetable editor. We'll have a
look in depth at this later, but this is
how you open it. Then moving on to the
bottom of the oscillator, we have the
aforementioned wavet position which
scrolls through the wavetable through
the different frames inside of the
sample that is loaded. We then have the
unison setting which determines how many
copies of these wavetables play. So you
can actually have multiple copies
playing over here and you set the tuning
relative between them like this. So
what's going to happen is is that the
middle one, the one that we see being a
little bit taller and yellow is going to
be tuned to the frequency of the note.
And then all other voices are going to
be tuned either slightly below or
slightly above that. Again, this tuning
amount determines how far that is going
to actually happen. So this is going to
be percentage of the maximum D-tune
amount. Next up, we have the blend where
we can blend between the central voice
or the side voices. So the lower or
higher tuned voices in case that you
have an even number, it's going to be
the middle two voices. So as you can
see, the middle two voices are now used.
And that is going to mean that one of
those voices is going to be tuned
slightly higher and the other one is
going to be tuned slightly lower. Now I
set maximum D-tune amount. The way that
you edit that is by going into this cog
wheel here. You can also set other
options for the D-tuning like the
different modes that it uses. Linear
mode is going to mean that every voice
is going to be equally spaced. Now the
next mode, super as well as exponential
are going to have them closer together.
If I see it exponential, you can see
it's closer. You can see they're more
towards the middle than the linear one
is. And then the inverted is going to be
the opposite where they're more towards
the outside. Finally, random is just
going to get you random positioning,
which as you can see just changes from
time to time. We also have an option to
actually stack this D-tuning. So you can
stack up one octave, two octaves, three
octaves, an octave plus a sevens, two
octaves plus two sevens, three octaves
plus three sevens. You can set one an
octave lower or you can set one two
octaves lower. And this is just going to
get you a wider frequency range with a
much fuller tone for dude sounds. Next
up, we have the stereo width because all
of the voices are going to be panned
separately left or right, which is of
course going to create a stereo width
effect. And if you don't want that, you
can of course set the width all the way
to zero. As you can see, you can also go
negative where you can invert the width
or invert the left and right channel.
Next up is the dune range. That is going
to be the maximum amount of dune that
can be applied which can actually go up
quite high to four octaves as you can
see and there's quite a lot of cool a
tonal sound design that you can actually
do with this. Next up you can add slight
changes to each voices for the wave
table position. So the parameter is
going to actually differ per voice and
the same is going to be true for rap one
and rep two which are going to be these
rap parameters which are going to look
at now. Is its
now warping is really one of the key
ways that you're able to change the
sound as you're able to actually make
changes to the wave table itself. And as
you can see over here, you can select
your different modes and then you're
going to have an amount over here. Of
course, these arrows are there for you
to quickly switch between different warp
modes. You can also already see that
sometimes an extra parameter over here
is available. But the main effect of the
warping modes are going to be coming
from this parameter over here, which as
you can see is also happening here. You
can see that that actually alters the
waveform quite significantly. So,
starting out with the first warp mode
that is available, that is going to be
the sync that I'm showing right now. As
you can see, that is the first one in
the menu and the one that we click to
with the arrows. And what sync does is
it allows you to pitch up the oscillator
while re-triggering it at the original
pitch that it was playing. Meaning that,
as you can see, we are increasing the
speed of the waveform, but it always
just stops playing and starts playing
from the exact start of the waveform
over here. Meaning that at this setting,
we're definitely duplicating the
waveform more than twice, but not three
times. As you may know, two copies of a
waveform in the same space as one copy
of the waveform is just going to mean
that one waveform is one octave higher
than the other waveform. But in this
way, you can kind of get in between
textures, which is really nice. And of
course, this also offers an easy way to
switch between octaves. So, for example,
if I set it exactly to two, we're going
to get two copies of the waveform. And
now in my sound design, I could modulate
this to, for example, go down to a value
of one. and therefore smoothly morph
between these two octave settings. Now,
because we're just cutting up the
waveform at any random point, what might
happen is that you have a setting like
this where the very end of the waveform
isn't actually at silence and you're
going to get nasty clicks. That is where
the windowing comes in, which you can
set up over here. So, more and more
windowing is actually going to fade
these edges to silence so that they
smoothed out. And that way you're not
going to get nasty clicks from the
waveform suddenly going from one
position and then circling around to the
start of the waveform where it's at a
completely different position producing
a click. The next warp mode is this band
plus mode which is going to kind of
stretch the waveform so that it squeezes
in in the
center. We also have band minus which is
going to do the exact opposite like
that. We then also have a combination of
both band plus and band minus. So you
can see we can go from the most plus
setting over here to the most minus
setting over here. And again, having
both options is nice for modulation if
you know that you're only going to go,
for example, into the plus direction,
you know that you're going to be able to
use this and be much more precise with
where you're setting the parameter or
where you're modulating to. And if
instead you want to modulate between the
negative and the positive, you also have
an option for that. The next warp mode
is going to be pulse with modulation. So
what this does is it just adds onto the
end and kind of squeezes the waveform to
the beginning like this.
And this is actually a very common sound
design technique in a lot of subtractive
synthesizers because it's a fairly
simple way of creating interesting tones
out of basic shapes and therefore it was
implemented in quite a few different
analog synthesizers. The next set of war
modes are going to be the asymmetrical
war modes. These are going to similar
kind of similar to the bend modes but
they're actually going to kind of
squeeze the wave from one way or the
other way. It's not going to squeeze it
this way in the way that the pulse
modulation did by adding stuff over
here. It is literally just going to like
stretch the whole waveform. So that
looks like this for the as plus and then
the other way for the as minus. And
again, we're going to have a plus and
minus variant as well if you want to
morph between both of them. What this is
going to do is it's going to flip the
waveform upside down. And here you can
set the position where that is going to
happen. So as you can see it goes
through it twice, but you can flip it
once and then at 50% and lower it flips
again. Next up we have the mirror warp
mode. What this is going to do is it's
going to take the waveform and actually
flip it. So this is mirrored to this
part. And then it's going to apply
something that looks very similar to the
asymmetric mode to it, but it's going to
apply it differently to the first part
as opposed to the second part. So that
looks like this. You can kind of see
that this still has that asymmetrical
kind of movement that we also saw with
the as plus and as minus warp modes.
Then next up, we get into something
really special, which is the remap mode.
As you can see, a little pencil opens up
here and when clicking on it, we get
this curve editor. What you can do here
is edit a time remapping curve. So this
is going to be the input time and this
is going to be the output time. What
that is going to mean if I set the warp
amount all the way up is that you can
see I can basically map time forwards or
backwards or I can create extra points
by double clicking and then mapping time
to wherever I want. As you can see, I
can also therefore create duplicates of
parts of the
waveform. Or I could even exclude
certain parts of the waveform entirely
by just moving this
down. Like if I only wanted, for
example, the first half of the table.
What I can do is I can do something like
this. Now, there's going to be many,
many more different ways of actually
editing the curves, but I'm going to
talk about those when I talk about the
LFOs because that is where you're most
likely going to use the more advanced
editing features. For now, though, what
I do want to say is that these kind of
curves also come with presets. So, you
can load presets over here, but you can
also shave your own shape. And then,
finally, for this one, there is a grid
size. Again, this will be a little bit
more important when we look at advanced
editing features. Just for now, know
that it's here. Now there's actually
four different versions of the remap and
everyone as you can see raises the
octave by one we can again see extra
duplicates of the wave table and the
reason for that is if I actually make
some changes here you can see that the
remap curve is actually applied
differently to different parts. So you
can see that it's applied one way for
the first three copies of the wave cycle
and then for the last one it is applied
differently and the same is going to be
true for remap 3. As you can see two
times remap forward and then this does
some kind of
inverse. And then here again we have one
version and another version. After the
remap modes we have the quantize mode
which is going to be a sample and hold
downsampling algorithm. So either sample
and hold or down sampling whatever term
that you wish to use they both describe
the same thing in that they're going to
make the waveform more and more blocky.
And what you're really doing with this
parameter is just setting the sampling
rate that is being applied for this
downsampling. So you can see that the
higher that you set that the lower the
sample rate is actually going to be and
the bigger the blocks are going to be.
And this type of war mode has a really
nice digital quality to it because it's
not possible in analog circuits.
Finally, we have the odd/even where you
can morph between odd harmonics and even
harmonics. So that means if you want to
leave the waveform unaffected, what you
have to do is you have to set this to
50%. So if I now go to off, you can see
it leaves it basically unaffected.
And then again, just like the band plus
minus or the asim plus minus, you can go
one way for one option and the other way
for the other option. Now that's going
to be the first category, these alt warp
category of warp modes. So next up we
have filters. So we have a low pass
filter and a high pass filter. Right now
for some reason it seems like the graph
is not actually updating or the display
is actually not updating. This is going
to be the filter cutff and this is going
to be I believe the steepness. So, these
are going to be non-ressonating low pass
filters and highp pass filters. Then, we
have almost all of the different
distortion types. There's actually going
to be two more different distortion
types which we're going to look at once
we look at the distortion in the effect
section. But these are all going to be
warp functions of the same algorithms.
But, as I said, just in the warp
mode, as you can see, for this one, it
is updating. So, you can see the
different type of clipping that it may
be doing. This is hard clipping. We have
diode distortion, another diode
distortion, and of course a whole bunch
of other crazy things that you can
do. Zero square is actually very
interesting because it distorts the
quieter parts, not that louder parts.
Rectify makes the waveform go all
down. Sign shifter again giving us crazy
shapes. Stobox a little bit more of a
tamer distortion type. Tape saturation
again a little bit tamer. and finally
the soft saturation which actually can
distort quite significantly as you can
see. And then all of the other warp
modes are going to be various
modulations between the different
oscillators. So we have our classical
FM, we have our phase distortion which
is going to be the same FM as we had in
serum 1. And then we have amplitude
modulation and ring modulation. As you
can see we have a whole bunch of
destinations. So we can choose FM from
B, FM from C, FM from the noise
oscillator, which is this little guy
over here, FM from the sub, which is
this little guy over here. and an FM
from one of the two filters. So, we can
take the output from one of the two
filters and actually use it as our FM
modulator or phase distortion modulator
or the AM modulator or the RM modulator.
As you can see, phase distortion also
comes with a self modulator. So, you can
modulate itself and this can result in
some really crazy kind of a tonal
sounds. Usually, phase distortion FM is
kind of associated with that because
that is where it originally was born
with the DX7.
But honestly, over the years, all of
these different modulation types have
shown to be very, very capable of
creating very cool different sounds in a
super wide range of categories. So, this
is definitely something where you want
to experiment. When it comes to the FM,
there's also some extra options over
here. We have through zero, which
determines how the phase is actually
handled when going from a positive side
of the cycle to a negative side of the
cycle. I was going to do this, but it's
better to explain it here. It will
actually flip the phase around when it
does that, when it goes from positive to
negative or from negative to positive.
And that has an impact on how at those
points in the modulation the FM response
is going to work and how that is going
to look like. And with this option
enabled, you're going to get more smooth
FM tones. So I've just quickly set up a
basic FM from
B. We can see we have a so over here and
a so loaded over here. I've just set up
the FM from B. And that is the only
setting that we
have. You can see that that is the tone
that we get if we set it through zero.
And then we have exponential and linear
which is going to be a different
interpretation.
[Music]
and then the linear
one. Of course, the exact tonality that
you're going to get is not only going to
depend on the mode that you set over
here, but also on a lot of the other
parameters that you're using and of
course the waveforms and all of that
kind of stuff. But this is one extra
option to just choose between the few
different flavors of FM. The final
option that we have in this warp
selection is to swap warps. So, if we
want to swap warp mode between the first
one and the second one, we can do that
like this. And you can see that all of
our options get flipped, including the
amounts. The final section of the
wavetable oscillator is going to be the
panning and the level. So, the panning
is going to determine how loud the sound
is going to be from left to right. And
then the level is going to determine how
loud the sound is going to be in
general. So, those are all the options
from the wavetable oscillator. I mean,
except the wavetable editor, but we'll
get there. We'll first check out the
multis sample over here. And this is
going to be an oscillator which is again
going to rely on audio files. But in
this case it is going to be many many
different samples. And what you'll also
need is an SFZ file which is going to be
the configuration of how those samples
should play. Luckily for us there's a
lot of different factory samples if you
want to check those
[Music]
out. You can see that for different
notes different samples are currently
being triggered. But I can also for
example lower my velocity a little
bit and then play a lower velocity or I
can play a higher velocity over here.
And this is usually reserved for
creating very realistic sounds because
of course every little inflection is
going to have a difference on the sound
and actually recording multiple sounds
for that instead of playing back the
same sample every single time is
actually going to capture all of those
differences. You can see that most of
the options have stayed the same. There
are a few differences. For example, you
have velocity tracking over here. This
is going to make sure that the velocity
is actually going to affect the volume.
So you can click that on here and set
how much that is going to happen. Since
this is a very common option for multis
sample samplings, they decided to do it
like that instead of having to set up a
modulation for it. The second parameter
which is different is going to be the
random over here. This is going to
determine the start position of the
sample that is being played. In this
case, we don't have this circular wave
frame thing which is going to be like a
small extract of a bigger sample. In
this case, it's just going to be the
starting point over the whole sample.
And then the final parameter that is
different is going to be the tambra
where you can select which sample is
going to be playing for different
pitches without actually changing the
pitch. So playing the same note
[Music]
now you can hear that it's trying to
play the same pitch. There was one that
was pitched a little bit higher but that
is just going to be inside of the
sample. But you can kind of think of it
as an offset between the MIDI notes that
are being used to determine which sample
to play and the notes that are being
determined actually how the pitch of the
sound should be. Moving on to the sample
oscillators, there's actually two ways
that we can get there. We can of course
just select the sample oscillator, but
we can also rightclick over here and
switch this to a single sample. So now
having switched it to a single sample,
you can see the waveform is showing. And
again, some of the parameters of this
oscillator are going to be slightly
different. The main gist of this
oscillator is that it allows for some
looping. Right now it is set to oneshot
modes but you can change the looping
mode. Over here we have the forward loop
which means that it's going to do as the
name says. It is going to move forward
through the sample, play back the whole
sample and then go back to the beginning
and play back the whole sample once more
and then do that infinitely until you
release a key. Reverse is going to do
the same thing but in reverse. We then
have forward and reverse which means
that it's going to play through the
sample like this and then backwards and
then forwards and then backwards. And
then finally, we have tilt, which means
that it's going to start from the start
of the sample, start playing up until
halfway, and then it's going to loop the
second half of the sample. So, if you
have a sample that is a nice transient
at the start, and then you have a
consistent tone towards the end here.
This is a nice way to make sure that you
can play notes that are as long as you
want. Right next to the loop mode, we
have the crossfade where you can
determine how fast it fades between the
start of the loop and the end of the
loop. So, you can kind of imagine what
this does. It is going to fade the start
of the loop in over here and then it's
going to fade the end of the loop out
over here. And the higher you set that
parameter, the longer that change is
going to be. Next up, we have the start
of the loop as well as the loop length.
Now, of course, because we are oneshot
mode, it's not actually going to show
anything. But if we go into for mode,
you can actually see the loop showing up
over here. And then we can set the start
of the loop, which is going to be the
starting position and then the total
length of the loop as well. Now, what's
interesting is that you can also set
this negative. So, you can have the
start of the loop at the end. Now, what
this is going to do is it's really going
to mess with the way that these loops
modes work. For example, now forward
loop is actually going to go in reverse
through the sample, but it's still going
to go forward because the start is here
and the end is here. So, it's
technically still going from the start
forward to the
end. Whereas, of course, normally if you
have it set to normal, it is just going
to loop for again from the start to the
end, but then forward towards the right.
So be aware of that fact that you can
actually have these kind of almost
inverted loops kind of thing. What you
can also have is actual starts and end
to the sample which you can just drag
out from here. So now you can see that
the playback starts over here over here
which you can also do is set the sample
end. So we can set the sample to end
over
here. And if we have it set to oneshot
mode then it's going to actually stop
playing. Now right now with the sample
as you can see there's a little bit of a
tail. So, one of the things that you may
want to do is do a little bit of editing
with the sample. That is all done
through the right click menu. So, we can
right click here, and you can see that
there's a couple of different snap
options. You have a zoom option. If
you're zoomed in, you can actually zoom
out because you can zoom in with the
mouse if you want to. So, for example,
if you're all the way zoomed into the
waveform, you just click like that and
you're restored to all the way zoomed
out again. We then have different snap
options which allows you to snap to
different things. We have snap to zero
crossing, snap to individual beats, and
snap to the entire loop. After that, you
can set if there's going to be a cross
fade at the edge, so at the start or the
end. That is going to be useful if you
have clicks in your sample. We can
normalize the sample. We can also
reverse the sample or trim the sample.
In order to trim a sample, all you have
to do is you have to slice out the part
that you want. And then right click,
trim, and that is going to act like the
whole sample. Finally, we have the slice
mode over here, meaning that you can
actually slice up the sample and trigger
different parts of the sample with
different notes. This is going to work
best with a drum beat. So, let me just
quickly get one.
Now, having found a drum loop sample, I
I don't know why I ran into my kitchen.
I actually have my drum loops right over
here. What we have to do is we have to
import it into Serum. So, as you can
see, right now, our drum sample is
loaded, this sample over
here. And then we're just going to right
click and turn on slicing. We can do
that by choosing either the auto mode or
the manual mode. I like to start with
auto. And as you can see, all of
transients are going to be detected. Can
zoom in and we can see that every little
hits of the drum is detected. But if you
want to add more slices, you can also
But if you want to add more slices, you
can also do that by setting it to manual
mode. So I set it to manual mode and
then I hold alt and click to add an
extra slice. I can also alt click to
delete slices. So really the right
workflow in my opinion is to just set it
to auto first. I'm going to set it to
auto. One of the things that you have is
like a detection level. You can set this
a little bit lower to detect different
areas. Zooming out, we can see what kind
of effect that is going to have. The
lower you set it, the more slices you
get. The higher you set it, the more
sensitive it is and therefore the fewer
slices you're going to get. And what you
may also see is while I'm hovering over
here, it shows you which notes need to
be triggered in order to play those
slices. So that means that by triggering
different notes we can play different
sounds and you can also do that over
here. Now that we are in slicing mode,
there are some extra options if we right
click. The play slice to end option
allows you to make sure that slices
actually finish playing even if you
release a note early. Play single slice
allows you to play an individual slice.
And then if you do that, there will be a
modulation destination somewhere in the
matrix where you can assign where you
can assign a modulation to and determine
which slice needs to be played.
Specifically, if you're going to go into
the oscillator, it is going to be this
single slice over here. So, if I quickly
set up a macro for that by going to
macro one here and then go back to the
oscillator, you can now hear that we can
play the individual slice with different
pitches. And turning up the macro will
change which slice is being played.
Of course, it is going to depend on the
modulation depth that you're going to
apply as well as how many slices that
you have. But this is a really cool way
to maintain the functionality of both
the slicing as well as the pitching
around. And you can imagine that you can
create some really cool complex machines
inside of different LFOs and other
modulators to find interesting ways of
playing different samples. The next
option allows you to set the root note
from which the samples should start
playing. So you can actually select the
different octaves in which you like
these slicers to play. And that is just
going to mean that the very first key is
going to be that key. And then it's
going to go progressively up. As you can
see, the send to selected clip option
will send it to the clip manager, which
we're going to see over here. This is
actually the clip mode. As you can see,
right now something is loaded. And that
is what that option just did. Of course,
we're going to look into the clip modes
in more detail later. For now, the last
option is autos sync to clip, which is
going to make sure that when you send it
to this clip here, if you make any
changes, any edits to the slices or
something like that, like updating a
timing, which you can do by setting it
to manual mode, and then, for example,
moving this around. If you make that
change, it will also be updated in here.
Right now, that is not happening. But if
I set this on and I make a whole bunch
of changes, we should see that update.
As you can see, this is now slightly
different. And again, if I make some
changes, if I hold, for example, alt a
few times and just remove them, you can
see that changes are being made here.
The final key parameter in the sampler
is going to be the scan option, which is
actually going to replace the wave tail
position. And what this allows you to do
is modify the playback speed of the
oscillator. So, by default, it's going
to be at 100% playback speed, but you
can make it go all the way to zero, or
you can have it play in reverse. And you
can also speed it up by minus 200 or
plus 200. If you want to have a greater
amount of speed control, you can do that
by right- clicking and then selecting
the range. We also have the reverse
option over here so that the playback is
going to reverse. We can lock the scan
rate to the BPM tempo, meaning that if
you're changing the BPM over time, the
scan rate is going to update. Finally,
we have the sample length to BPM, which
means that the scan knob is actually
going to work in musical intervals. The
last option that is new for the samper
is going to be in the unison settings
where we will see the span is replacing
the waveetail position setting meaning
that you can have different playback
speeds for different voices which is
sure an interesting sound design
technique. Now let's move on to the next
oscillator type which is going to be the
granular oscillator. As you can see this
is also looking very very complex and
there's even so many parameters that we
need the second page here. But actually
the granular oscillator is much simpler
than it first appears because what we're
essentially going to do is we're going
to again chop up the sample into
multiple different slices. But in this
case the slices are going to be very
dynamic meaning that they can start and
stop at any point in time. And what is
going to happen is most likely you're
going to be playing multiple different
slices at the same time creating kind of
textures out of different samples and
then randomizing different parameters
for different slices that you're playing
to create an interesting soundsscape. So
just with our drum loop now in the
default, what we're going to get is
something like
this. So what you can see is happening
is that it is playing through at once.
And while it's doing that, you can
actually see the multiple playheads that
it's using for every slice. And you can
see that there's multiple slices playing
at the same time. Now, as I said, this
is based on these slices. And actually,
these slices are called grains. And what
you'll see is that we have an extra
window amount over here which is looking
very very similar to a crossfade. Now
this crossfade is still here because
also the main looping functionality is
still
here. So you can hear it is still
looping at the playback. But what we can
also change is how for each of these
slices, for each of these grains, the
volume comes in over time and then goes
out over time. So we click on here where
we get this different shapes that we
want. So we can select a whole bunch of
different shapes of different windows.
I'll morph all of them so that you can
see them. There's some very cool things
towards here as well where it starts and
then it just quickly stops or it stops
and then quickly starts towards the end.
Here we have this amount over here which
as you can see determines how much of
the window is actually being applied. Of
course that is going to depend on the
window that you're using and how it kind
of moves up and down. We also have
skewing options over here. So we can
skew it forwards or backwards. And both
of these parameters can be randomized
for every gray. Now within the lower
settings over here, what we'll find is
we will find the different playback
settings. And this is really what is
going to bring the granular oscillator
to life. We start with the playback rate
which is again being done by the scan.
This one can be randomized by this
direction amount. Over here we have the
density which is going to determine how
many grains are going to spawn every
second.
We're going to be able to determine the
length of each grain in
milliseconds. Again, this parameter can
be randomized with this randomization
over here. As you can see, it is linked
in the interface. The same is true for
the panning. So, we can randomize the
panning for each of the individual
grains that are playing.
which as you can hear creates a nice
stereo effect. We also have the level so
we can change the level for each of the
grains. Again, we can also change the
length. The other one that we see over
here is the pitch. So, we can actually
alter slightly the pitch in semmitones
of each individual grain.
The last two randomizations are going to
be the direction which is going to, as I
said, randomize the scan
here. So, you can see we get a whole
bunch of different playback speeds,
including reverse ones. And then
finally, we have the offset, which is
going to be how far away from the
playhead position it is going to play.
Meaning that if we set it all the way
up, it's just going to start playing
anywhere in the
sample. Finally, as you can see, we also
have our warp modes again, and we can
randomize for each grain the value of
the warp modes here, which is also an
excellent way to get extra tonalities
out of different grains and create a
more broader soundsscape. There are
still a few more options, mainly the
spawn pattern over here, which is going
to determine where and how the
individual grains are going to spawn.
So, we can set that, for example, to
random to really just have them spawn in
random
places. I believe it's going to depend a
little bit on the size of the actual
sample, and we may have a little bit of
a longer sample, which means that it
doesn't actually spawn throughout the
whole thing. The final thing that is
interesting is that there's also an X
and Y controller. So, if I right click
here, we can show XY control. And now we
can see there's a little bit of a dot
here, which is going to make it so that
you can manually play the granulator
here and basically determine manually
where the slices start to
play. Again, in this case, we have the
offset sides. So, if we start it right
here, it's going to be closer to
it, especially with the direction all
the way down.
And the cool thing is is that you can
right click this
here and then go into the Y-axis where
you can set any of these other
parameters as a secondary parameter that
you can control as well. So let's say
that we set the random offset here. We
now
have as you can see two parameters that
we're controlling over here. And this is
mainly nice to start experimenting
because I don't think there's an easy
way that you can modulate just this
point. And even then these points are
just assigned to different points over
here which you can then just directly
modulate if you want to. The final
oscillator type is the spectral
oscillator which as you can see also
comes with a really nice display. What
this is going to do is it's going to
break up your sample in different FFT
partials and then it allows you to
change properties for those FFT
particles before an inverse 4A transform
is applied and you get back into a
normal sound again. Well, I say normal
but usually when it comes to spectral
synthesis it does have a very unique
characteristic to it. It is a little bit
like smoothed out but also very digital
sound because it is only something that
you can do in the digital domain. And
there's actually two interesting ways
that you can process the sample within
this oscillator. The very first one is
through the filter. If we click on here,
we have a filter that we can
[Music]
play. We can already hear that slight
smoothing of the transients which
spectral synthesis is known for. And
here within the filter we can see that
we can actually edit the curve and
update the curve like
[Music]
this. And now this curve is being
applied. We can see that both in the
window over here as well as actually in
the sample. So we can see this little
cut being present in the sample. And if
I remove that it updates and it goes
away. There's two parameters that come
with this. We have a mix control over
here which mixes in this filter. We also
have a cutff which allows you to move
the filter up and down the frequency
spectrum or technically the FFT spectrum
but really it is nice to think of this
as a waterfall frequency spectrum with
the lowest frequencies below and the
highest frequencies above and this axis
being time. On the side here we have low
pass and highp pass filters. So as you
can see this would be a low pass filter
and this would be a highp pass filter.
You can see though that it's very very
sharp so it's going to be unnatural.
[Laughter]
Like this is literally going to emulate
a brick wall filter in the sense that
it's going to go up to a certain
frequency and right before that
frequency it is going to be at full
volume and right after that frequency it
is going to be all the way silent. If
you want that a little bit smoother you
can right click here and do smooth it.
Now you can see it kind of smoothly
comes down.
There's also another option which is the
post warp which means that it is going
to apply after the warp modes. That is
because we have extra spectral warp
modes in here. As you can see, there's a
whole range of them and we also have
some of the other warp modes as well,
but these are just going to be the
normal ones. Do note that some of the
warp modes are missing and that is also
going to be the case in some of the
other oscillators. So, just to run
through it, I believe that the old warp
is only available for the wave table.
So, if I go to multis sample, it isn't
there. If I go to normal sample, it
isn't there. And if I also go to
granular, it isn't here. And then, of
course, spectral is going to be the same
thing, but then we're going to have
these spectral warp modes. The first one
is going to be D-tune plus minus, which
is going to tune up or down individual
partials. You can already see it having
effect because it is going to be in a
normal position if you set it to 50%,
meaning that you can either decide to
tune it up or down. And this is going to
have a a very strong effect.
[Music]
There's also a secondary parameter here
which shifts a little bit of a different
part of the FFT
information. Honestly, in this
particular case, it doesn't seem to be
too drastic. I've had points where it is
almost all being shifted by this
parameter. I've had points where it's
parameter. I don't really know what the
criteria is and it sometimes seems a
little bit arbitrary where it decides to
have one part be shifted by this
parameter and and other parts be shifted
by this parameter. So it feels a little
bit random where it's making those
decisions to what to shift with which
parameter. The next warp mode is
smearing which allows you to smear out
the frequency spectrum. So this is going
to make it sound a little bit smoother.
If you do this though too much, it is
going to actually become silent.
And then here we have a secondary option
which seems to do the same
thing. Honestly, I haven't figured out
yet what the differences are between
these two parameters. So, let's just
move on to the next war mode. This is
going to be the spread plus minus which
allows you to either spread out the FFT
information or smoosh it more together.
And that is going to happen vertically.
Of
[Music]
course, in this case, the secondary
parameter is just going to be a general
shift up or
down. And just like many other warp
modes, if you want to have the normal
sound, you're going to have it in the
middle
[Music]
here. The next one is going to be
harmonics, which is going to extend the
harmonic content kind of like a
resonator.
[Music]
We then have subharmonics, which is
going to generate lower harmonics for
the signal that we have. We can already
see it starting to happen here, but you
can really turn it up like that. And
then it's just going to be
boommy. So, if you want to create some
really bass, heavy sounds, this is one
way of doing it. We next have the
spectral gate, which is just going to
allow the loudest parts of the sound to
come through.
You can hear you can get some really
cool almost underwater like tones out of
that. We have the robotize which is
another kind of smoothing type of
sounds.
I honestly have found that this seems to
have a very minimal effect on whatever
we apply it to. I've experimented with a
few different samples and I really
haven't found a good sample to actually
show you what this is doing. Next up, we
have the shift, which allows you to
shift up all of the partials.
We have mirror, which allows you to have
them come in as a mirror from the
[Music]
top. It's almost sounding like a more
extreme version of downsampling. And
that is because it is actually
technically taking all of the frequency
information and putting it in there. It
isn't just generating like an individual
spike there. And therefore, the more
that you turn it up and the more copies
that you make, the more aggressive it is
going to be in the high frequency. So,
this can really get really high
frequency heavy if you're not careful.
And this is also one of the reasons why
you might want to set this to post warp
so that you can later come in here, do
something like this, and then smoothen
this out and actually cut some of this
out again.
So now you don't have that really
extreme brightness that you get if you
don't do that. Next up, we have the peak
follow mode which is gradually going to
remove the quietest peaks of the sample
and it's actually going to keep peak
continuity over sample. So if you have
any harmonic content that is very long,
it is going to try to treat that as like
one block as opposed to spectral gate
which is just going to remove the
quietest part irrespective if it's part
of a peak or not.
We then have plus and negative octaves
of a sound. So you can morph between the
normal version of the sound and an
octave
[Music]
higher or an octave
lower. There's also this HMX version of
it which has a slightly different way of
mixing between the two.
[Music]
And of course also for the
negative. Next up is the harmonic sweep
which is going to make harmonic copies
of the sample higher up the frequency
spectrum.
[Music]
We have shepherd which is going to
generate shepherd tones. Again, this is
going to have a secondary parameter.
This is going to be for the walkthrough
of the shepherd stone. So, this is going
to allow you to cycle up the shepherd
stone by one. You can see this frequency
is going to rise up to this frequency
here. And of course, a shepherd stone is
known for that continuously happening.
So, in this case, we would add an LFO
here like this.
[Music]
And there you have your shepherd stone.
But you can also set the frequency over
here. So you can have it starting denser
and
[Music]
lowered. And this is a really cool way
of creating those infinitely rising
pitch effects. What we also have is a
shepherd's W, which is going to be an
inverted version. As you can see, this
has cutouts as opposed to just keeping
the parts that is going to be
shephering. So in this case, it is
actually going to be removing frequency
content and that removal is going to be
like shephering up the frequency
spectrum.
I can almost describe it as the inverse
phaser version of a shepherd stone
because it also does have a little bit
of a phaser kind of quality to it in my
opinion. Anyway, the next warp mode is
going to be this coms here which is
going to emulate a comb filter.
[Music]
[Laughter]
We have a bit shift mode which allows
you to pitch shift the sample up and
down.
[Laughter]
[Music]
I was also hoping that it would cross
fade at the higher points, but that
doesn't seem to happen for some reason.
As you can see here, it's kind of
crossfade between the original and not
having the original and just having like
a pitch shifted version. But when going
up above 50%, that doesn't seem to be
the case. And again, that does mean that
this is a bipolar warp mode, meaning
that 50% is going to keep the sound in
its original state. And then you can go
either down from there or up from there.
Next up, we have the phase twist, which
is going to lock all of the phases of
the different harmonics
here. In this case, this might not be
the best sample. So, I'm quickly going
to change it to say like a flute or
something.
[Music]
You can hear that with the phase twist
all the way engaged, you're getting a
very very stable kind of
[Music]
sound. And in this case, you can hear
there's a little pitching happening with
this extra variable parameter.
[Music]
Next up, we have the format. Here it is
probably handy that we again have a
little bit of a drum
loop. As you can hear, it gets a little
bit quieter, but the main thing that
it's doing is it's emulating a format
filter, which is going to be the sound
of a mouth moving and like talking and
having different vowels and whatnot.
You'll see what I mean when we talk
about the format filters that are going
to be in the filter here. The final two
options are very very interesting as
they require a different oscillator to
work. So we can take oscillator B here
and say that we load a different sample
in here. What it's going to do is it's
going to use this sample as a mask on
this sample over here.
Keep in mind I have the level set all
the way down here. So we're not actually
hearing this sample playing. What we're
hearing is this sample being subtracted
from this sample over here. And then we
can do the same thing, but instead of
subtracting, we can also vocal it.
So this is the frequency content of this
sample with all of the volumes modulated
at any given point in time based on what
we have over here on the content over
here. So we're basically imprinting
almost like the volume information on
the frequencies of this sample. I mean
if you know how a normal vocoder works
it is going to be very much like that
but it's going to be happening in a
spectral way. So like the process is
slightly different but just practically
speaking you can think of this as
actually just v coding with this signal
over here. And as you can imagine, heck
you told me a week ago that you could
use Serum as a vocoder, I would have
laughed in your face. But right now, it
is just completely possible within this
new update. Now, finally, we have gone
through the main oscillator. So, we can
have a look at the other oscillators,
which are going to be the sub oscillator
and the noise oscillator. Starting with
the sub oscillator, we have parameters
for octave and coarse pitch here. And we
can choose from six different shapes. We
can also set the phase or the starting
position of that shape and then set the
panning and the level here. So this is
really just meant to add a little bit of
extra stability, usually an octave or
two below your main sound that you're
playing so that you have a nice stable
sub. And again, this can be routed over
here. So you have your drop down for
your routing. In this case, it is not
going to a filter, but we can send it to
a filter and then move it left to right.
We can also send it directly to the main
effect scene or directly to the output.
So this is going to be directly to the
output bypassing any of the effects
even. And then we can also send it to
nowhere. This is going to be useful if
you only want to use this oscillator say
for I don't know the spectral v code
from the sub oscillator but you don't
want to actually hear this oscillator
then you can set it up like this so that
it's not routed to anywhere and you
don't actually hear it. Now to the right
here as I said we have the noise
oscillator which is actually basically
just a sampler. As you can see it is
currently set to loop mode but we can
also set it to oneshot mode meaning that
it's going to play it only once. And
this sampler is loaded with a whole
bunch of different noise files which you
can choose over here. You also have
different other files like attacks for
kick drums and that kind of stuff. You
have inharmonic sounds over here which
are some really cool textures. And then
you have really cool atmospheric stuff
as well. This is basically just an
entire path already in here which you
can load up and use as part of your
patches. You can also load your own
custom sample or you can open up the
file browser here in the place where the
sample that you have currently loaded is
stored. So as you can see it just
directly takes me to the path where the
current sample is loaded. And then you
can also go in here and add your user
samples in here so that they are
directly going to show up in this folder
over here. There are some non-sample
options in here. You can generate some
noise through this color option here.
You have access to white, pink, ground,
and geer, which is a noise type I've
never heard of. So that sounds very
interesting. All of the noises come with
a different filter. So you can see that
the pitch controls are now removed. And
we also have a stereo control over here.
Normally this is where the phase control
is. So if I go back to a sample, you can
see that we have the starting position
of the sample as well as a randomizing
the starting position of the sample so
that it randomizes for every note that
you trigger. And as I said before, we
have fine tuning as well as the overall
pitch here. And then we have panning and
level for the output. So those are all
of the oscillators. Now let's have a
look at the filters which you're going
to find over here. I've quickly reset
the syn so that we have an initialized
patch so that we can hear exactly what
the filters are doing. But again, you
can turn it on over here with the knob
and then you can switch between the
different filters that you want to see.
You also have routing options over here
where you can send it to different
outputs including the other filter. And
then once again to one of the two FX
buses just like with the oscillators.
You have the selection over here. But in
this case, of course, you're selecting
filter types. You again have arrows to
move between them if you want to. And
then we have the display. If you right
click on the display, you have three
different options. You can have just the
frequency response, which is just this
curve. You can also show all of the
frequencies if you play a sound.
And then finally, if you want to see the
phase response of a filter, you also
have an option for that. After that, we
have easy routing switches for all of
the oscillators. So if you want
oscillator A to go through filter one,
which is already set up, you do that
over here. We can do the same for
oscillator B, C, and the noise
oscillator, as well as the sub
oscillator. And you can see it updates
over here. We have the key tracking
option over here, which is going to mean
that the filter is going to react to
incoming MIDI nodes and adjust its
filter cutff accordingly. The filter
cutff can be set over here together with
the resonance. We have a little bit of
drive which can be nice for some of the
nonlinear filters. But if you want
cleaner versions of those nonlinear
filters, there's also an option
available for that which is going to set
the input gain to minus 24 dB and then
compensate in the output gain with a
boost of 24 dB. Again, we have a
variable control over here. Currently,
it's set to fat, but it's going to
change depending on the filter type. And
then we have filter panning, which is
going to apply the filter more to one
side of the stereo field. We have the
mix of the filter, so just to mix it in
or not. You can see that represented in
the graph as well. And then finally we
have a final level over here which is
just set in dB. Now going through the
different filter types we of course have
our basic filters in the normal section.
We start with the moch emulations of low
pass filters. And then we have our
classical low pass filter, classical
highp pass filter, band pass filter,
peak filter and notch filter.
[Music]
We have these multif filters over here
which are going to be combinations of
the basic filters. So we either have a
combination of two different filters
where the variable control is going to
be the cutff for the second filter and
they're going to share a resonance
control. See we have a low pass and a
highp pass. So the low pass can go up
and the high pass can go up and as you
can see they share the resonance. But
then you also have these morphing
filters over here which morph between
three different filter types depending
on the morph parameter. So it goes from
low pass through band pass to highp
pass. And of course that is going to
depend on the type of morph that you're
using here. So this is between a notch,
a peak, and then a band
pass. The next category of filters are
going to be the flanges, which really
are not just flanges, but also com
filters and phasers. These are filters
that are designed to generate many
different peaks inside of the frequency
spectrum. So this com filter over here,
as you can see, it's all wobbly, meaning
that it's going to generate multiple
different
peaks. As you can imagine, in terms of
phase response, this is going to have a
quite heavy phase response. And that is
also why we hear that pitching effect
when we move the filter cutff.
We have a few different combination of
these including ones that have
selectable frequency ranges. So this is
a low version and then we have a high
version as well. And the same is going
to be true with your basic flanges here.
So this is just a basic flanger
frequency response being
[Music]
this. We have the opposite of it as
well. And then we have all of our low
versions and high versions.
Next up, we have the different phasers
here. So there's different steepnesses
and pull amounts. So this is just a one
pull
phaser. And then if you want to have
multiple pulls, you can go up to
four. And for the highest pull amounts,
there's also low versions and high
versions over here. This one is a
combination of both.
[Music]
The final two filters are a phaser
flanger combination filter. I believe
the technical way that it works is that
the phaser is inserted into the feedback
chain of the flanger.
[Music]
And as you can hear, all of these
filters are definitely changing the
sound more than just your standard low
pass or highp pass filter. And
especially once you start modulating
them, there can be some really
interesting sounds that can come out of
this. The final category of filters are
going to be all of the miscellaneous
filters. That is going to include all of
the old miscellaneous filters as well as
all of the new silver filters. We start
with some basic EQ bands. As you can
see, we have a low shelf with a dB
amount. Also, low shelf 12, which is
just a little bit of a steeper one,
especially because I've set a higher
resonance
here. Then we have our just simple peak
band EQ over here. Again, you can set
steeper resonances if you want to and of
course move it around and drive it a
little bit. And then we have the high
shelves, which is just going to be the
opposite as the low shelf.
The ring mod filter and ring mod 2
filter allow for ring modulation.
Actually, ring mod 2 is going to be two
ring modulators with the spread amount
determining the distance between each
other in terms of frequency. So, you can
see you can get some really nice like
interactions between them and almost
like cancellings and whatnot.
[Applause]
[Music]
The sampled and sampled minus are going
to be downsampling algorithms. So this
first one is just your basic
downsampling filter.
[Music]
And then sampled minus instead of being
just your normal downsampling algorithm,
it is going to take the input of the
algorithm and subtract that from the
output. So that means that we're just
going to get the down sampled signal and
not the original signal in there.
[Music]
As you can hear, this can be a really
cool filter if you want it to sound like
the sound is almost breaking up in an
interesting digital way. The next three
filters are all based on all pass
filters. So, these are going to be the
coms, all passes, and reverbs. There's
also some delays involved in the
internal circuit, meaning that there's
this dampen option over here, which
allows you to dampen the high
frequencies in the internal feedback of
that delay. And all that that really
means is that these three filter types
are going to be amazing for phase
shifts.
[Music]
The French LP is a very colorful
nonlinear filter which comes with a
secondary resonance control.
[Music]
So you can hear you can generate some
really cool distorted tones out of that.
The German low pass is known in the
business as a zero delay feedback
filter. Now if you're really interested
in filter design and all of the
mathematics behind it, then that may be
an interesting thing to Google. but
otherwise it isn't. So if you're not
interested in it, just think of it as a
low pass filter with its own unique kind
of flavor and
[Music]
response. We have the add bass filter
which is a phase rotated low pass
filter. What that means is that that's
going to have a unique phase response.
And the interesting thing is is that you
have a through parameter over here which
is basically like the mix but the dry
signal is going to have the same phase
rotation meaning that your lower
frequencies aren't going to cancel out
when you're mixing it in through this
way. So this is a great filter type to
put in parallel and just add a little
bit of extra low end to certain sounds.
The next set of filters are going to be
the foreman filters. There's going to be
three types over here which are going to
emulate different vowel
[Music]
movements. Here both the cutoff and the
forement are working together to
basically change the vowel shape and the
cutoff isn't really I would say
responsible for the center position of
the filter.
[Music]
The band reject filter is the opposite
of a band pass. As you can see, it just
removes a certain area. And you can set
the width parameter over here, meaning
that you can go really wide if you want
to.
You can imagine this kind of bass is
really useful for something like
neurobase design because you can scoop
out that mid-range, keep the low
frequencies in here, keep the high
frequencies in here, and then distort
that again to gain the warmth back. And
then if you modulate it, you get that
classical neurobase movement. The next
set of filters are going to be the
distorted combs. These are going to be
either low pass filters or band pass
filters. So we have a category 1 low
pass and band pass and a category 2 low
pass and band pass. The difference
between version one and version two is
that version one is going to have a
positive comb filter and version two is
going to have a negative comb filter. We
saw that before when we looked at the
flanges where we have a positive comb
and a negative comb. So one is going to
be like this and the other one is going
to be flipped around. But these filters
of course combine the aspect of a low
pass and band pass filter with these
comb filters.
And as the name suggests, you're going
to get some distortion as well. And we
have the drive set nice and high. Again,
if we want to test out something like
clean mode, that is where we do
[Music]
it. Let's go a few octaves
lower.
[Music]
Honestly, I feel like it's getting more
distorted with clean mode on than with
clean mode off. So, I don't know if this
is flipped in a
way. But either way, there's also, of
course, the band pass version available.
[Music]
And then the final two filters in this
folder are going to be the scream low
pass and scream band pass. Now screen
filters are based on having a relatively
high feedback in the internal delay of
the filter. But what that really means
in practical terms is that this is going
to have a screaming sound specifically
when you drive it.
[Music]
1. And again, there's a low pass version
available as well as a band pass.
[Music]
and also again with this filter I feel
like the key mode is set the other way
around that with it active we get
actually a lot more distortion. The
final category of filters are going to
be the new filters that are included
with Serum 2 but not with Serum 1. But
the first one of those is the WSP
filter. This is a morphing filter
between a low pass, band reject, and a
highp pass. So, we have the low pass
here, band reject here, and then highp
pass. And in the manual, it says that
this filter is designed for its high
buzzing tone. So, let's see if we can
get that out with a little bit of
[Music]
resonance. It does sound very buzzy
indeed. The DJ filter is based on the
free XR plug-in DJM filter. So that is
this one over here. And this is based on
both a low pass and highpass. So we have
a highp pass when the cutff moves this
way and a low pass when the cutff moves
this way. Other than that, of course,
you have your resonance and your drive
in
here. And I think a filter like this is
really useful in say Serum Effects where
you can use it for transitions. Yes,
there's going to be a whole other plugin
called Serum Effects that we also have
to talk about. But going back into the
filters, the next filter that we see is
going to be the diffuser. This is going
to act very much like the disperser by
kilohz as it's also based on multiple
stages of all pass filters with you
being able to set the amount over here.
So you can see what that does to the
graph. Starts out fairly
[Music]
basic. The more stages that I set, you
can hear the more lasery feeling our saw
wave gets.
[Music]
It almost has a little bit of a zap to
it at the start. That is because of all
of the phase shift that this filter is
doing. It's actually not really showing
in this graph, which is interesting. I
would actually say that this is more
like the phase response and this feels
more like the frequency response because
it's based on all pass filters which are
known for changing the phase without
changing the frequency response. The
next filter is the MG leather which is
based on a transistor leather filter. So
that's a particular type of circuit used
to implement filters in analog gear. And
this version of the transistor filter is
not going to have any distortion with
it. So it's actually a very clean
[Music]
filter comes with this very interesting
parameter. As you can see, the smooth
isn't really chasing the graph. Instead,
what is going to happen if you have any
modulation assigned to the filter cutff
or the filter cutff is moving in any
other way, it is going to smooth out
that movement. The next filter is going
to be the acid ladder, which is going to
be based on a diode ladder instead of a
transistor ladder. What that means is
it's going to have a slightly different
tonality, and it's going to be
specifically designed for acid sounds,
as the name suggests. This is really
where we get that classical acid sound
from.
The EMS ladder is going to be based on a
VCF filter. This is again just a
different circuit type which is going to
result in practical sense in just a
different tonality for your low pass.
And then finally, the final ladder
filter that is going to be available is
going to be the MG Dirty. This is going
to be a distorting version of the MG
ladder filter. So, this is going to be a
nonlinear version.
[Music]
And as you can hear with the paint
parameter over here, you can get some
really strong distortion. And actually,
this pain parameter is described in a
very interesting way in the manual,
which according to them literally
implements the physical act of holding a
lighter to the filter circuit and moving
it closer and further away from it. I
mean, I have no idea why anybody would
do that other than creating these
interesting sounds. But it is an
interesting discovery that they made it
and then decided to actually implement
that and actually physically model that.
And honestly, that goes to show what
kind of care they take to add
interesting filters to this update of
Serum. The next filter is also going to
be very, very interesting. As you can
see, we have quite a bit going on here.
We see a drawing over here. We see this
filter graph opening up as well. What
this filter is going to allow you to do
is draw in custom peaks. So, we click
here to get the peak
editor. Let's set the drive a little bit
lower. I've set the resonance also a
little bit lower so that it doesn't get
so buzzy. That is because the resonance
is going to be applying a gain to all of
the different peaks. So, it's actually
just going to scale these peak upwards
and downwards. But you can design your
own filters here. Right clicking, you
can actually change the filter type that
you're using. So for example, we can
have a band
here or we can have an allp pass
filter. Do a little bit of phase shift
with that if you're interested in that.
Then next up, we have this moving area.
That is because there's not just one
filter over here, but there's XD4. So
let's go into version two here.
set up a different filter and then we
can morph between one and two and it's
actually going to morph those filter
types. Let's for example add a highp
pass here to make it a bit more
interesting. Another bell and maybe a
high shelf as well. If I can get a shelf
in
here. It doesn't seem that there are any
shelves available in here for some
reason. So, let's just keep it the bell.
And then let's do something else with
this other bell here. And then we move
between them.
I think this is going to work best if in
version one we also set a highp pass
filter here. Say with a little bit of
resonance like
this. Fortunately, in between it doesn't
seem like it's staying in there. Maybe
that has to do with the fact that these
don't have highp pass filters. So, let's
see what happens if all of them do.
Maybe just with the way that the
morphing is
implemented. No, it doesn't seem like
you can keep highp pass filters and low
pass filters in there. But still, of
course, you can create four unique
filters and morph between them in
interesting ways. With regards to the
other parameters, we have the filter
cutff, which is just going to be a
general offset to the left,
right? And then we have the resonance
over here, which as I said is going to
be a gain or cut for all of the
[Music]
peaks. We have the overall drive going
into the filter. Of
course, then we have smoothing again,
which is going to be again modulation
smoothing. And I can emulate that by
turning the smooth all the way up and
then just really fastly moving the
filter cutff.
So you can see that it takes a little
bit of time for the filter to actually
move and it just has like a basic
minimum speed to it. How fast it can
move from left to right. The next filter
type is com 2 which are going to be two
comb filters that are combined together.
The best way that I can describe this
filter is if you're familiar with the
RoboCom filter from Filterverse, which
reminds me if you want to see me
deconstruct filter verse in the same way
that I'm doing now with Serum, there's a
video available for that. But in
essence, it is going to be two comb
filters combined into
one. So here's the first one, and then
we have a frequency for the second one
as well.
You can kind of see them interfering
with each other and causing cool
patterns. The last two filters are going
to be based on a classical piece of
software called synthesizer expander
module. So we have a morphing filter
going from a low pass to a notch to a
high
pass. And then we also just have a band
pass version of that filter. So this is
just a regular band pass. no morphing
whatsoever. But again, it's going to be
based on this particular filter from
this particular piece of software. And
again, in practice, that is probably
going to mean that it has a slightly
different tonality to it. So, those are
all of the filter types. Let's now move
on to the mixing window, which we can
click, which we can get to by clicking
over here. You can see that you have
some basic controls over all of the main
parts of the synthesizer. We have all of
the oscillators over here. We have the
filters over here, and then we have all
of our effects buses. And really the
main point of this page is for easy
routing. So you have an overview of all
of the routing. Just like with the
original oscillators and filters, you
have the ability to turn them on and
off. Right below that we have routing
information. So again, you can choose
where it's going to go. If it's going to
go to one of the two filters, if it's
going to go to our main FX bus, if it's
going to go to our direct out over here,
or if it's going nowhere. When you have
it selected to filter, you're of course
going to have your filter mix here. So
again, you can choose between everything
going into filter one, a combination of
the two at whatever percentage that you
want, or everything going into filter 2.
And then you have individual sends for
FX bus one and FX bus 2. So if you want
to do parallel effects processing, this
is the way to do that. So in essence,
you're going to have two parallel buses
going into a bus in serial, but you can
actually change that to any type of
configuration that you want. So for
example, if you want to hook them all
up, what you can do is change this to
bus two. Now everything that goes into
bus one then goes into bus two and then
goes into the main. And that means that
you can have different effects on all
three of the buses and send for example
a part of your synth directly to the
main bus, a part of your syn directly to
bus two and then a part of your synth
directly to bus one. So now as you can
see the filter is going to main because
it's set to main here. But it's of
course going to be splitting in bus two
with this amount and oscillator A is
going to go to bus one with this amount
as well as to the filter which is then
feeding the main bus as well as bus two.
Now you can also send bus two into bus
one but of course you cannot really
combine the two. As you can see that
switches this one to the main one. What
you can also do if you want more
parallel buses is set both of them to
direct. So we set this to direct and
this to direct. By default this is set
to direct because of course after the
main it is going to go directly to the
outputs. And that means that we now have
three parallel buses on which we can
load effects so that we can have
different parts of the sins being
processed differently without one
feeding into the next one feeding into
the next one. So say that oscillator A
is responsible for like a top melody,
oscillator B is responsible for like the
chords and oscillator C is responsible
for a baseline. You can process each of
them differently according to the needs
of the sound. Now some other controls
that you have over here is for the
filters. You have control over the
filter cutff as well as the resonance by
just basically moving this graph around.
We have control for the panning. In this
case, this is going to be just a simple
oscillator panning. So it's going to pan
the oscillator left and
right. And the panning for the filter is
going to be equivalent to this pan over
here, which is going to affect the
offset of the filter cutff position
between the left and the right
channel. So you can hear one moving up
and one moving down for one channel. And
of course, if you move the panning in
the opposite way, it's going to be the
other one moving up and the other one
moving down. We also have mix controls
as well as level controls. We also have
level controls for the oscillator, of
course, but no mix. And then finally, we
see this little icon over here which is
indicating where envelope one is being
applied to the sound. Something that
we're going to learn when we talk about
the modulators is that envelope one is
going to be responsible for the volume
of the sound. And therefore, by default,
it is already going to be assigned to
the volume. And that is going to happen
somewhere. It depends on where it is.
So, if I turn off the filter, you'll see
it will happen on the oscillator or at
least it should be happening on the
oscillator now.
So, it turns out I slightly
misunderstood what this parameter is
doing. It is actually allowing you to
untie filters from the envelope. So, you
can hear that has a little bit of an
effect. If I set the release
But by default, the oscillators are
always tied to the envelope. So if we
don't have this, it is always going to
be this
behavior. The final thing that is
interesting in this mixing window is
what happens when you right click over
here. We have the ability to disable
pitch tracking for individual
oscillators. Of course, we have some
resets as well as MIDI learning options.
And then we have copy and copy with all
of the modulation assignments. Once we
copy, we can of course also paste, but I
haven't copied anything, so we cannot do
that yet. What I do want to show is that
this is also available here. So, I can
copy this one and then go here and
paste. And the same is going to be true
for the filter. If I right click, copy,
go in here, paste, we get the same exact
filter. And it's nice that you're able
to do the same thing from the mixer
window over here. Moving on to the
effects window. As I said, there's three
different buses. You can switch between
the buses over here. This is going to be
your main bus, which is going to be your
final output. Meaning that there's
nothing going to be happening after this
main bus, meaning that the last effect
is the last thing that you're going to
hear before it goes to the actual output
of the synthesizer. And then, as we saw
before, bus one and bus two can be
inserted relative to that, either in
parallel with the main bus or in series
in front of it. There's a little button
over here that allows you to actually
extend the effects range, so that you
have a little bit more of a view of the
actual effects that you're applying
here, but of course, you lose the
ability to edit the modulators. you're
still going to be able to assign them as
they're going to show up over here. One
thing to not is that that's not going to
be the case for the macros. They don't
actually show up with the ability to be
assigned, which is a little bit of a
shame. I would have loved to just have
like eight little areas over here that I
can just drag from and assign as well.
Again, we're going to see the modulation
system in much more depth later. So,
don't worry if you don't understand what
I'm talking about right now. But back to
the effects themselves. You can select
effects over here by adding modules. As
you can see, just a window opens up with
all of the different effects. If you
want, you can also load up entire effect
chains here. So there's different
presets for different effect chains and
you can also save your own presets once
you have an effect chain created. Now
going over the effects themselves. I'm
going to start at the very top with both
here. This is going to be a frequency
shifter, although I like to personally
think of it as two frequency shifters
which separately frequency shift the
left and the right channel. We have the
ability to mono the input over here,
meaning that you can use it as a
stereizer because it's going to sum it
to mono and then make it steer again
through the frequency shifting. We have
a shift amount over here which is going
to determine how much shifting is
actually going to take
place. And as you can see this is a
bipolar control. So it works in opposite
directions meaning that it's going to in
one side shift the left channel up and
the right channel down and the other
side it's going to shift the right
channel up and the left channel down.
The amount by which that happens is
determined by the range here.
[Music]
[Applause]
So you can see with higher ranges we get
a much more extreme effect. The
direction is going to determine which of
these two frequency shifters is going to
be used. So the behavior that I've been
describing up until this point happens
when you set the knob exactly in the
middle. But you can also select one of
the two frequency
shifters. And now you can hear it is
functioning like a mono frequency
shifter. Of course you can go to the
other shifter as well by going the other
way. We have the width control over here
which is going to determine how much
stereo widening is applied to the
sound. So if you want to be fully mono,
you can turn it down all the way to
zero. Now this module also comes with a
delay which you can set up over here.
Here you can set the time in
delay. We also have a feedback for that
delay. And you can set the timing in BPM
as
well. So now it's tied to a musical
[Music]
notes. We have the balance over here
which is going to determine the delay
offsets between the two different phase
shifters. So if you want
that, you're going to have one frequency
shifter going to the delay and now the
other or in
between. And you can also blur the sound
by this like almost coarse type effect
here with this blur
parameter. So this can create some
really crazy almost reverb style tails
as well.
[Music]
And then the final two parameters are
going to be the mix, which is going to
determine how much of the wet signal
versus how much of the dry signal we're
going to
get. And then there's an overall general
volume balance. This is going to apply
both to the dry as well as to the wet
[Music]
channel. Honestly, if there's really
something that I would like for my
effects, it is the ability to right
click here and just set it to wet only
mode. So that the level is going to
apply only to the wet sound. That way,
we would finally be able to correctly
set up the dry wet for nonlinear
effects. That is very technical, but I'm
going to explain that a little bit later
when I talk about the distortion.
Speaking about distortion, let's move on
to the next effect, which is going to be
the chorus. What the chorus is going to
do is it's going to create four copies
of your sound. Two for the left channel
and two for the right channel. And it's
going to pair these two copies and apply
different delays to them. Those delays
are modulated. So we have the modulation
rate over here which again can be BPM
synced to have it in musical terms or
can just be free running to have it in
frequency. Then we have the delay amount
for the first stereo pair and the delay
amount for the second stereo pair. We
have the depth amount which determines
how much these delays are going to be
modulated. So this is just going to turn
up these delay amounts which again are
read in milliseconds. We then have the
feedback which is going to determine how
much of the output of the effect is
going to be fed back into the input of
the effect. Turning this up will make it
sound more resonant and just overall
will make the effect more
pronounced. And then finally we have
filtering where we can switch between
low pass filter and highp pass
filter. And then the knob is going to be
your simple frequency that you can set.
So you can set it to be the whole sound
if you just have the low pass filter
turned all the way
up or the highp pass filter all the way
down. And generally speaking, what
you're going to get from a chorus is a
nice bit of stereo widening and just
overall like smoothing and warming of
the sound. So this is definitely one of
the more useful effects in there. The
next effect is also going to be very
useful because it's going to be the
compressor. What the compressor allows
you to do is it allows you to set a
threshold above which the sound is
actually going to be turned down. The
amount of turning down is going to be
determined by the ratio over here. So
every decibel that you go above the
threshold, it is going to be turned down
four to one in this case. Meaning that
you would actually need to have four dB
of volume above the threshold in order
to get one decibel of volume above the
threshold in the output. Now the
compressor is actually time based,
meaning that it doesn't start and stop
instantly applying those like ratios
above the threshold. Instead, it takes
in this case 90.1 milliseconds to start
working and 90.1 milliseconds to stop
working. And the attack is measured from
the moment that the sound goes above the
threshold while the release is measured
from the moment that the sounds goes
below the threshold. Again, then finally
we have the makeup gain. So if you want
to compensate for the compression that
you're doing, you can turn up the whole
signal and therefore you get a more
squash sound because essentially that is
what the compressor is doing. It is, you
know, squashing the sound together
volume-wise and then you can turn it up
to just have more loudness out of the
same peak level. Now this is when the
compressor is working in single band. If
it actually works in multiband, we get a
whole extra range of parameters over
here. In this case, we actually get two
different linked thresholds for three
different bands which you can actually
see being represented in the graph here.
Currently, we see the high bands over
here. So, this is where above the
threshold downwards compression is going
to be happening. We also have these
lower bands where below the threshold
upwards compression is going to be
happening. But that doesn't happen until
we set the below parameter. So, if I
turn this up, you can see that is
represented in the graph as well. And we
can see this kind of compression. It is
taking the volumes and compressing them
upwards. Whereas this is taking the
volumes and compressing them downwards.
Now you can actually set the threshold
for each band separately if you click
here in the middle and move it down or
up like this. And you can also set
compression ratios by just dragging over
here. So you can see the actual
compression ratio here and here. You can
also see that this is going to be able
to do downwards expansion which is the
opposite of compression where you
actually increase the dynamic range as
opposed to decreasing it. Finally, the
last few parameters are going to be the
low crossover and the high crossover,
which determines where in the frequency
spectrum we're going to go from the
lowest band into the middle band by this
crossover and from the middle band into
the highest band by this crossover. And
then the final three parameters are the
output gains of each of the individual
bands if you want to compensate them
separately. The next effect in the list
is going to be the convolve. This is
going to be a convolution reverb,
meaning that you're going to need to
select a file, which you can do by
clicking here. You can select one of the
factory impulses like cabinets or any of
the reverbs like these weird reverbs but
also just like standard reverbs here. Or
you can load your own impulse response.
It says load your own impulse response
but little sound design tip here. It
doesn't have to be an impulse response.
It can be any sound. It is of course
going to be very very unpredictable if
it's not an impulse response. What the
sound is actually going to do, what this
effect actually is going to do because
it is designed for impulse responses.
But there's still potentially some
really cool sound design that you can do
by not loading an actual impulse
response. Now, let's say that we just
load a standard like reverb here. So,
the large hull for
example. Let's turn up the mix a little
bit so you can hear it
better. Then this parameter is going to
be the size parameter here. This is
literally going to update the length of
the file.
See here, you can hear that it's
actually like slowing down some of the
dynamics in the file. You can hear
individual peak one and individual peak
two
here. And if we set it really short, of
course, all of that is going to be
compressed to the very
start. And we're going to get a really
really small almost early reflection
style reverb. We have the overall
tonality of the file. So you can make it
react more to high frequencies or low
frequencies.
You can hear we're literally removing
low frequencies like this. And this way
we're going to remove high
frequencies. Another cool option is this
minimal phase over here, which is going
to create a minimal phase frequency
representation of this curve. So it's
going to take all of the frequency
information in this impulse response and
turn it into an instant impulse response
like a cabinet simulator would do.
So this is just going to apply the
tonality of the
[Music]
sound as opposed to the actual tail of
the
sound. We have a pre-delay option which
is going to delay the wet signal so that
you can have a transient go through
cleanly first and then have all of the
reverb if you want
to.
Again, as you can see, you can tie this
to BPM if you want to set it in musical
notes instead of just frequency or like
milliseconds. We have attack and decay
parameters which are going to apply to
the file over here. So, an attack is
going to attack at the start here and
it's going to morph the start. And then
the decay is going to make sure that it
fades out nicely. So, you can see it's
fading out more and more and it becomes
sharper and sharper. We have a parameter
here for dampening of the high
frequencies.
So, this is also going to make your
reverb darker in the same way that
turning down the tone does. And then
finally, we have the impulse response
gain, which allows you to literally just
turn up the volume of this file or down
if you want
[Music]
to. And really, when it comes to
convolution, this is a massively
powerful tool. So, I don't think that I
can really show you all of the things
that it is capable of because, of
course, it is going to depend on the
input file that you have. And you can
literally have infinitely many different
input files, all kinds of samples and
stuff that you can throw in there to
just see what is interesting and what
sounds cool. So really, this is the kind
of effect where you really just need to
dive into it yourself and experiment
with it to get an intuition of how it
actually works. The next effect is a
little bit of the opposite like that as
it's going to be a simple delay. We have
access to three different delay modes.
We have the normal mode where we just
have a left channel delay and a right
channel delay. We have a ping- pong mode
where we have again a left channel delay
and a right channel delay, but they're
going to be feeding into each other. So,
the left delay feeds into the right
delay and then the right delay feeds
into the left delay. Meaning that you
get this alternating effect between the
left and right
channel. Whereas the normal delay is
just like a stereo
effect. And then finally, we have the
tap delay where again the left channel
is going to go into the right channel.
But in this case, they're not playing
left to right. So, they're going to be
playing in mono. And what is going to
happen is that the left channel is not
going to have any feedback. And the
right channel does have feedback.
Meaning that you're able to set both
like a starting delay for it. So, how
long until the first delay hit happens,
and then how fast the actual tail is
going to play.
[Music]
So if we set this for example very long
and this very short and turn up the
feedback which is just going to be the
length of delay because the more that
the output feeds back into the input of
the delay the more that it's going to be
[Music]
repeating. You can hear that it takes a
bar for the delay to actually work and
then we get all of those tones kind of
morphing into each other at 16 notes.
Now currently the timing is set in
musical notes but that doesn't have to
be the case as you can set it to
milliseconds. What you can also do is
link the left and the right delay. So if
you want to have them the same value and
you don't want to update both of them,
you can easily do it like this. There's
an offset down below as well. So this is
just going to be a percentage offset
where you can have it or you can set it
up to dotted. As I said, the feedback is
going to be how long the delay rings out
for because it's going to be feeding
back into its own input. And then
finally over here we have the filter
which is controlled both by the
frequency left to right as well as the Q
which is basically how much of the
spectrum are we actually capturing. So
you can just exclude a part of the
spectrum, usually both a little bit of
the low end and a little bit of the high
end so you can get a smoother way of
mixing in your delays with your original
sound. The next effect is going to be
the distortion. Now there's 18 different
distortion algorithms. You can choose
from the algorithm over here and
sometimes there will be an extra button
that appears over here that allows you
to edit some of the algorithms. Now I'll
quickly go through some of the other
parameters first and then I'm going to
explain every single distortion type and
how it works. That is because I quickly
need to explain graphs and stuff like
that in order to actually make it
understandable what distortion is doing.
So we have a filter over here which can
be inserted either before the distortion
or after the distortion. By default it
is off. It can morph between a low pass
filter to a band pass filter to a highp
pass filter. And you have frequency and
Q values over here. And then we have the
drive which is going to change the
transformation curve as well as the mix
which is going to mix between the
transformation curve that is currently
displayed in the graph and a linear
curve. Now that may not make sense. So
let me quickly go and talk about
distortion a little bit. And in order to
do that, I'm going to go in here and
actually open up the X shaper. As you
can see, this is one of the ones where
we get some extra parameters. And the
parameters that we get are actually
these two graphs here. So we have a
graph A and a graph B. Now what this
graph is going to represent, it is going
to be this quarter and inversely this
quarter of the graph over here. And what
I'm able to do is for any input volume
of this graph, I'm able to remap it to
any other output volume. And this is
going to be an instantaneous process
which is going to act on all of the
individual samples. If you're familiar
with music production terminology, you
may have heard of the term wave shaper.
This is exactly what a wave shaper would
do in the sense that you're able to set
up this transformation shape. So, for
example, I can double click here. I can
double click here. And you can see it
happening in the graph as well. Right
now, we're editing the A graph. So, we
want to set the drive all the way down
to get the exact representation that we
see over here also happening up here.
And we can see this little peak here
being this little thing. So if I move
that around, if I jibble that a little
bit, we see that. And then we see this
bigger block here, which is going to be
this block. So again, if I move that
around, you can see that represented
like this. Now, if I move all the way
over to B, what we can see is that it's
currently a linear graph. So as you can
see, it's just a straight line down,
meaning that all of the input volume is
going to be remapped to the exact same
output volume. That is also what the mix
is doing. So if I move it back to here,
you can see that the mixes between
linear and our shapes here. Of course,
that is handy if you also set up a
custom shape in B and you still want to
be able to mix it in. In that case, the
drive is not going to do that for you,
but the mix is going to. Now, knowing
how this graph works, we can start to
interpret it when we talk about the
other distortion types. So, let's just
go into the tube distortion. And what
we'll see is if we turn the drive up, it
is just going to make things louder by
literally just bulging out this graph
here. This is, as you can imagine, based
on the way that analog tubes actually
saturate and distort. And this is going
to generate only odd harmonics because
of that. The reason why that is the case
is because we have a symmetry between
the graph at the upside and the
downside. For those that don't know,
this is going to be the positive cycle
of the wave cycle and this is going to
be the negative side of the wave cycle.
Later on, we'll also see an example or
two of graphs where that isn't the case
and therefore we're also going to be
generating even harmonics. But for now,
the odd harmonics continue with the soft
clipping and the hard clipping. So this
is soft clipping, meaning that we're
just clipping off the highest part of
the waveform and we're softly
approaching that. especially if you set
it up like this for example. And then we
have the hard clipping where you can see
at a certain point we just start to clip
and we don't make it go any louder and
you can determine where that point is
going to be. We have the diode over
here, diode one and diode 2 which is as
the name imagines based on diodes in
circuits and how they distort. We then
have this very crazy graph for the
linear fold which as you can see is
literally just like triangles folding up
and becoming more and more aggressive.
As you can imagine with this, we get a
very aggressive type of distortion
because we're really quickly remapping
for when the volume changes just a
little bit. Like a small change in the
input volume can have a massive result
on where the output volume is going to
be. So you get some really messy sounds
out of
[Applause]
that. Same is going to be true for the
sinefold, but this is going to have a
little bit of a smoothing effect. As you
can see, these like triangles are
smoothed off a little bit and you get
more of a sign shape to
[Music]
it. Still a very aggressive distortion
sound though. The next one is going to
be a zero square distortion. This is
also going to be a very aggressive
distortion because it's going to act on
the quietest part of the sound. Can see
that over here because here in the
middle is going to be silence. Again,
input volume is a horizontal axis,
meaning that this is going to be
positive input volume and this is going
to be negative input volume. And what
you essentially see is that the lowest
volumes are going to be remapped up to
higher volumes starting over here. And
therefore, it is literally going to take
the quietest part of the sound and turn
that up, resulting in a very, very
aggressive
sound. I'm just quickly going to lower
the resonance on here because it is not
really helpful.
can hear what kind of strong distortion
we get from it. And you can also hear
some artifacts when we're actually
fading out. Our next distortion type is
actually a digital distortion which is
going to be downsampling. If you look at
the graph here, it makes a little bit
less sense what is happening because it
is kind of shifting in weird ways. But
essentially what we're doing is lowering
the digital resolution of the audio
file.
The next distortion type is going to be
our first asymmetrical distortion. So
here you can see that the curve is
different from the top part than the
bottom part. What this means is that
we're also going to be generating even
harmonics, meaning that you're going to
get a much warmer sound of this kind of
distortion. And it's not going to be as
sharp as other distortions, say the
diode or the tube distortion. The
rectify is going to be a very strong
distortion because you can see that it
takes the whole positive part of the
wave cycle and flips it into the
negative. So all of the positive input
values are going to become negative
input
values. And this is going to mean that
this type of distortion can result in a
little bit of DC offset. So if that is
the case, then just set this to post
highp pass filter. Something like
this. And you're no longer going to have
the DC offset because that lives at the
very left of the frequency spectrum.
From a very technical standpoint, DC
offset is actually a frequency of zero
hertz because it's going to be a flat
line of volume, not at silence. Right? I
feel like maybe we're diving a little
bit too much into the technical, but if
there's something that you want to
research, I would like to give you like
tangents and stuff that you can research
from. So, if you don't know what DC
offset is, maybe have a little bit of a
Googling session and try to find out
because it is very, very important in
sound design because it can generate
this really low rumble that can be
really annoying to deal with if you're
not removing it with, for example, a
highp pass or a DC blocker. The next
distortion type is the one that we've
already seen, which is the X shaper, but
we also have the X shaper asymmetrical.
In this case, what is going to happen is
that we're going to have access to the
whole graph. So, we can see that our
shape is now represented one to one on
the graph. That means that from this
point on the input and output volume are
measured from here. So here we have 0 dB
going into the positive volume. Here we
go into the negative volume. And then
we're able to remap both the positive
side to positive volumes to different
positive volumes as well as to negative
volumes. Or we have the negative side
and remap that to positive volumes and
again to negative volumes as well. And
again you're going to have two different
shapes that you can morph between and
you can edit the different shapes over
here and over here. The next distortion
type is the sign shaper which is this
really cool kind of double sine wave
like graph to it. See if we turn this up
can see what kind of almost double sine
wave it gives. We have these really fast
sine waves going on over here and then
we have this almost like slower sine
wave going through it in an interesting
way. And you can hear that this is also
a very interesting distortion sound.
Next up, we have the stom box, which
isn't really a distortion. I would more
classify this as a saturation as it
isn't that
strong. And the same is going to be true
with the tape saturator, which is going
to have a slightly different graph, but
is again going to be more of a saturator
than a distortion. For those that don't
know, saturation is just distortion, but
less of it technically.
So, as you can hear, just like a slight
beef up of the sound, like a slight
tonality change, but not really any
aggressive new frequencies being
introduced here. What does introduce
aggressive new frequencies is the new
overdrive. This is another one that has
an extra parameter. In this case, it is
the stacks, which determines how many
stacks of overdrives are laid on top of
each other going up to 60. And you can
hear that this creates some really,
really aggressive distortion.
can down some really cool different
tonalities
here. You can hear what kind of cool
interactions this is getting with the
release still as well.
And then the final distortion type is
actually the soft saturator which does
say saturation but I feel like you can
get it to
distort. Like this is getting into the
territory where we're really just
altering the wave and we're getting a
much sharper sound. So I would almost
classify this as distortion at its
highest drive. But at lower drives you
do indeed just get a little bit of extra
coloration to the sound.
Which reminds me, as you can see, I'm
just bypassing the effect over here. So,
this disables the effect, but you can
still hear the output going through
it, right? It's not being affected here,
but it's also not blocking the output.
We're not like muting it in any way. And
of course, with the bypass turned off,
we are going to have the actual effect
of the distortion here.
This is much easier than, for example,
say that you have set a custom mix,
always going back here and turning the
mix down to hear what it sounds like
without and then having to set it back
to the exact same value. This is just an
easy one-click solution. The distortion
took a long time to explain, but the
next few effects are going to be a
little bit easier. We have the
equalizer, which is going to be a low
band, which you can set to low shelf,
low peak, or high pass or low cut,
whatever you want to call it. We have Q
factor for it here. We have the
frequency for it here. And we have the
gain, which is only going to act on the
shells and the beaks. And the same is
going to be true for this high band
here, but instead we have a high shelf
and a low pass or a high cut, whatever
you want to call it.
Again, and this is just going to be, as
you can imagine, your standard EQ type
deal. The next effect is going to be the
filter, which is going to be very, very
similar to the main filters in that it's
going to have every one of those filter
types. So, you can see all of the same
filters in here that we saw before. It
used to be the case that the filter
cutff could only go up to 16K for this
filter, but in this new version, the
filter can go up all the way to
22.050, which is actually going to be
Nyquist for anyone that is working at
44.1K. So, that is really cool. That is
actually a personal favorite feature of
mine that we now have the full range of
frequencies available over here. The
flanger effect is also a little bit more
of a basic effect with just very few
parameters. What this is going to do is
it's going to create two copies of the
sound and then it's going to apply a
slight timing offset to them so that
they phase cancel and create interesting
peaks and trough in the frequency
spectrum. We've seen those peaks and
troughs before with the actual flanger
filters over here. So have all of these
flangers, this is basically what the
flanger is going to do to the frequency
spectrum. And because the flanger is
being modulated by this rate here and
this depth, what you're going to see is
this spectrum kind of moving around as
if you're modulating the filter cutff up
and down. So, let's turn this off. I'm
also quickly going to go in here and
make sure that all of this goes to main.
And this is turned down here so that we
just hear a saw wave going through the
flanger. And you can hear that kind of
moving almost windy effect here. Of
course, if you want a stronger effect,
you can turn up the feedback. Again,
this whole process is based on an
internal delay and therefore you can
loop the outputs back into the inputs to
get a stronger response.
You can also hear that the left channel
and the right channel are doing
different things. And the offset between
the left and the right channel is
determined by this phase here. So if you
want to have them do the same thing, you
just turn this all the way
down. And now you have a monoflanger. Of
course, also if you turn it all the way
up because 360° and 0° is the same
thing, but you can go anywhere in
between to get a nice offset.
[Music]
The next effect is actually two effects
in one. This is the hyper as well as the
dimension. Both of these are stereo
widening effects. So that is why they're
combined together. The hyper is going to
be a unison generator. So as you can
see, we have up to seven voices here.
And then we can set a rate at which the
pitch differences between them are
modulated as well as the overall
D-tuning amount. So the maximum amount
of D-tuning being done by this
modulation, you can imagine that's being
equivalent to the D-tuning over here,
but instead of all of these voices
staying static in the position that we
see them uh with respect to like the
overall tuning, the overall D-tuning,
what they're actually doing is they're
like moving in between there. Finally,
we have a re-trigger option over here,
which means that if this option is
selected, all of the notes restart from
the same pitch and then start drifting
away in pitch so that you get that nice
kind of laser sound.
[Music]
see here you have that nice like laser
zap. But if you don't want that, you
just turn re-trigger off and you always
get like a
unison. We also have the dimension which
I personally like to think of as an
early reflections generator even though
it's technically not that. It is
actually based on some delays as well.
And you can just set the amount of delay
here. But in this case, because it's a
size, I like to think of it as the size
of the room that you're emulating
because it has this really nice like
delayed sounds which almost feels like
the early reflection actually takes some
physical time to move through the room
and then get back to you and you're
actually hearing
it. And of course, at size all the way
zero, it is actually going to be
instant. So then it just becomes a nice
extra stereo widening effect. The next
effect that we need to talk about is
going to be the phaser. This is again
going to be similar to the phaser
filters that we saw in here uh in the
flanges and an inphaser. So here we have
a one pulse phaser, a two pole phaser, a
three pole phaser and a four- pole
phaser. You can see that it just
increases the amount of spikes and
troughs that there are. And in the
phaser over here, we can actually go up
to 18 pulls. So 18 of these spikes here.
Again we have a modulation rate which
can be set to the timing of the song so
that it's project synced or we can set
it to be free running and set it in
frequency. We actually have two depth
amount here. The first one is for the
modulation depth. So the modulation how
much the modulation is being
applied. So here you can see that we
just have a static
phaser and now it starts to move.
And then the second deaf here is going
to set the distance between the
poles. So this is just giving you a
slightly different tonality to the
sound. We have the frequency which is
going to be the center frequency around
which this phaser is modulating. So
again we have a phaser here. Imagine a
center frequency and then it kind of
like modulating around it depending of
course on the depth. And here you set
the center frequency of where that
modulation is happening. We again
because this is based on internal delays
have a feedback parameter which is just
going to make the effect
[Music]
stronger. And again because the left and
the right channel are offset, we have a
phase which is going to determine the
offset between the left and the right
channel which if you want again to have
a mono phaser, you just turn this to
zero or
360° or you can have a left right offset
with the phase anywhere else.
The next effect is another bigger one.
It is going to be the reverb. That is
because there's five different reverb
algorithms. So, as you can see, we can
go through them here. And again, we have
arrows to move between them. As you can
see, these algorithms comes with
different parameters. So, I'm going to
have to explain all of the parameters
for all individual algorithms. We'll
start off with the plate algorithm,
which is going to be the default that
opens up and the first one in the list.
And this is going to emulate your
classical plate reverb. For those that
don't know, in like the 70s and even the
60s, maybe even earlier than that, when
they want to create reverb, one of the
ways that they could do that, is to have
a big metal plate and then have a
speaker on one end and a microphone on
the other end and literally play the
sounds through the blade so that it gets
kind of smoothened out by the actual
physical act of the plate vibrating and
then it gets recorded again and then it
will have this smooth like reverb sound
to it. So all of the different reverbs
are going to have a low cut and a high
cut to remove lower frequencies or
higher frequencies from your reverb.
This particular reverb is going to have
a size parameter which actually going to
determine the length of the
reverb. Let's turn this up a
bit. We have a pre-delay which is going
to delay the wet signal. So that again
you're going to be able to have say like
a transient coming through first and
only then having the reverb come
[Music]
in. We have dampening of the high
frequencies so that the high frequencies
don't stay as
bright. You hear a very dark reverb and
now we get a very almost unnaturally
bright reverb.
Finally, we have the stereo width.
Because a blade reverb used to be
originally mono, you can emulate that by
having a zero width here. Now, you get a
fully mono reverb, but you can also make
it wider if that is what you
want and just have like a more natural
reverb sound with the left and the right
channel having different reflections and
whatnot. The whole reverb is going to
emulate a hull type room. So, that is
going to be a very long deep room and
that is going to result in this being
very good for very long reverbs. So if
you want a very strong like very
extended reverb sounds, this is one of
the algorithms that does that
best. As you can hear, you can get some
massive reverb tails out of that. So
definitely be careful with muddiness in
the mix and that kind of stuff with this
reverb. In this case, the size doesn't
determine the length of the reverb, but
instead it determines the size of the
hole that we're emulating. So that is
going to have some effect on the actual
size of the reverb but also on other
parts of the reverb like the tonality of
the reverb. We can have a pre-delay and
then we have a decay which is also
responsible for the length of the
reverb. You can actually set it in
seconds but it's also going to use the
size parameter together with this decay
to actually calculate the final length
that you're going for. Finally, we have
this spin over here which is going to
change the delays that internally are
used for this reverb and actually
modulate all of those delays. So you can
set the modulation depth and the
modulation rate for that over here. If
you don't want any of the modulation,
you're going to get a more flatter
[Music]
sound. Whereas, if we set a little bit
of
modulation, you can hear we get a little
bit of a smoothing of a sound and it
also just slightly changes the tonality
of it. The vintage reverb is really good
for generating more old school warm kind
of reverbs. And one of the cool things
about this reverb is that you actually
have control over the early reflections
versus the late reflections. The size
parameter once again just sets the
length of the reverb. In this
case, we once again have a pre-delay.
And then we also have the length here in
milliseconds. Again, it is actually
going to use both the size and this
decay of here to calculate the final
length. As I said, we're able to control
early reflection separately. That is
where the ER size comes into play. We
again have dampening of the high
frequencies. So, if you want a little
bit more of a muffled natural sounds,
then this is the way to do that. And
then finally we have diffusion A and B
over here which are going to work
together to set up the diffusion.
Diffusion A is going to be the length of
the diffusion and diffusion B is going
to be the dampening of the high
frequencies of the diffusion. And you
can think of diffusion as like an extra
stage of reverb almost like it almost
acts like a reverb after a reverb in a
way. Finally, this reverb is being
modulated with a chorus. So as you can
see we have both rate and depth amount
for the chorus here. Next up we have
nitrous which is going to be a multiode
reverb. As you can see, we can select
the modes over here, and these are just
going to be different tonalities for the
reverb. The interesting thing about this
reverb is that this is one of the two
reverbs where you have control over the
actual feedback. So, this is another
different way to actually calculate the
size, right? A longer feedback is going
to result in a longer reverb size.
As you can hear, interesting things are
happening with this reverb. We again
have a pre-delay as well as a diffusion
stage over here. And the modulation on
this reverb is again being done by a
chorus. And then of course, the main
gist of this is that you're going to
have different modes which are going to
have different sounds and different
tonalities.
[Music]
You can hear you get a really wide range
of different tonalities. And with the
chorus ups especially, what you can do
is you can just play a short note into
it and then just have the chorus kind of
generate this moving almost texture for
you. The final reverb is basin. Now I
would almost qualify this as not really
reverb because it sounds really strange
to
me. As you can hear, it's fully mono and
it's not really like smoothing the sound
in a natural reverb way. It's just
almost delaying the sound.
[Music]
But it's definitely an interesting
effect, especially if you're modulating
something like the size, which results
in those pitch changes. Again, the
modulation on this reverb can be a
chorus. So, you can also set up like a
very strong chorus on
this, which is also going to sound very,
very similar to just a modulation on the
size. By the way, the only thing that I
would find cool with this particular
reverb is if there was like a whiff
parameter as well. I don't really like
the mono sound or the sound of mono
reverb. It just sounds unnatural to me.
But given that this doesn't really sound
like an actual reverb to me, I think it
is still going to have some creative
uses. The next three effects are going
to not really do anything on their own.
Like technically they are, but from a
practical stance, you're not going to
just have a splitter in here without
anything in that. And that's because
this is actually an FX host. So as you
can see we have a low channel here and a
high channel here. And you can frequency
split between the two different
channels. And you can affect the low
channel here. So this is going to affect
just the frequencies below this
frequency. And then here the highs we
can say convolve it or add a distortion
to it. And then this is just going to
happen on frequencies above this
frequency here. The other splitter
allows you to set up three different
frequency splits. So this is useful if
you want to have lows, mids, and highs
being processed differently. The reason
why I say that is because you could say
like, oh, if I wanted to split more, I
could just add another split. But you
can actually only have one split per
chain. So, one split here, one split
here, and one split here, which means
that three bands is the maximum amount
that you can split any signal into,
which means that you can have a mono
component and the side component, and
you can process those separately. And
then the final effect that we're going
to see is this utility over here. This
is useful for just having a low pass
filter, a highp pass filter. We can mono
the lower frequencies. Here we have an
overall width control, a panning
control, and then on the left here,
something that I forgot is polarity
inversion. So, this literally is just
going to take the waveform of, for
example, the left channel and like flip
it upside down. So, left flip here and
then a right flip. So, those are all of
the effect types. Now, one of the things
that you may have noticed is that we
don't have a list of predefined effects
over here anymore like we had in serum
one. And that's because you can have as
many as you want. So I can have just one
after the other after the other after
the other and just play with it and just
do as much as my CPU can
handle. So Serum is now much more
capable of processing your sound fully
and that is going to be really cool for
preset makers and preset users alike
because that is going to mean that we're
going to be able to make much more like
versatile and mix ready presets. So now
let's have a look into the modulation
system. I'm quickly going to open it up
over here. And just so that we have some
parameters, I'm going to open up a
utility here. So modulations are things
that you apply to parameters and they're
usually described as allowing you to
change the sound over time. But
honestly, with the amount of different
modulation sources that do different
things, that is not really a full
accurate description. So I would say a
better description is any change in
properties of the sound is done for
modulation. And what that is going to
mean is that you need to link your
modulation sources with the parameters
that you want to be modulating which you
want to be changing. And just some of
the modulation sources are available
over here. These are the main ones that
you're going to be using. We start off
with the macros which allow you to link
multiple parameters to a single
parameter. So as you can see I've just
assigned it by dragging it and then I
can edit over here the amount of
modulation that I want. So again we drag
it over to our parameter. Now we have it
set to two parameters. By default, it
loads up with the maximum modulation,
but you can of course change that. And
now, what is going to happen if I turn
up this macro is that both of those
parameters are going to be changing with
the same
strength. So, as you can see, as the
knob travels up, the parameter is
actually moving around the ring here and
moving around this ring here. So, these
are going to be your modulation depths.
Now the second modulation sorts are
going to be your envelopes. Now these
are going to be like changes over time.
As I've already discussed, envelope one
is going to be linked to the output
volume. And the way that an envelope
works is that it takes an amount of time
to go up to the maximum level. So up to
the maximum modulation amount. In this
case, this is defined by the attack. And
this will be very easily audiable. If I
turn up the attack, you can already hear
it in the volume.
And you can also see in the graph that
it's taking some time to go to that
maximum value. Then we can determine how
long it will stay at that maximum value
with the whole parameter here. So this
will extend and you can see that there's
an extra point there. That is because we
also have a decay stage which is
determined over here. You can see we're
setting a second length and then we can
set the actual value of that decay stage
in the sustain here. This will be the
value that is being held by the envelope
as long as you're maintaining a note. So
for the start of the playing of each
note, it is going to apply this curve to
any modulation that you set to it or in
the case of envelope one to the volume.
And then once you release a note, that
is where we get into the release stage
which is determining this final curve
over here. So again, you can turn up the
length and lower it as well.
And what you could also see is if I
release it prematurely, it is still
going to use the same length, but it's
going to start at whatever height it is.
And then go down to zero modulation
mount exactly within this time over
here. Now, you can also just drag points
around like this and also change the
curvature or the path that is being
taken by any of these stages. On the
right here, we have zooming. So, we're
able to zoom in and out like this. Or we
can lock it so it's always going to show
the entire shape. Meaning that if you
change this, it actually makes
updates like this and like this. If you
want to have these timings in actual
notes, you can do that over here. So
now, as you can see, it switches to
notes. Sometimes it shifts around a
little bit and then it also updates the
milliseconds. So now if I, for example,
wanted to have a curve like this, where
I set this to an eighth note, this one
to an eighth note, let's set this to an
eighth note as well. And let's set this
to an eighth note so that it takes an
half note for this entire envelope to
play like this.
Now, if we go into the milliseconds, we
can see that they're all actually
updated to the same value, which is
actually going to be exactly 1 over 8
notes in milliseconds for this
particular project BPM. Now, there's a
few more right-click options. We have
the grit. We can set that to either time
or beats. So, now it's time in
milliseconds or we can set that to
beats. And because, of course, we have
set this up with one over eight notes,
we're going to get exact beats here,
which means that all of our points are
going to be lining up with lines. The
second option has to do with the legato
behavior and that is behavior describing
how two notes interact when they're
playing together. So normally you can
hear that each note has its own
envelope. But if I play a second note
while the first hold is being held with
this option enabled, you'll hear that it
will actually take the envelope of the
first note and just continue from where
that is. So if the first note is already
in the sustain, the second note will
actually start from this sustain point
over here.
And this is going to be a setting that
will be very useful together with the
global legato settings which we'll see
later. So moving on to the LFO now. I
would say that this is the main
modulator that you're going to be using
inside of Serum. At least for me that
is. And that is because this device
really can do everything that you need
it to do in a timebased sense. So by
default the LFO is a looping modulator
meaning that this shape is going to be
looped depending on the time that we are
setting over here. So let's quickly
assign it to a parameter so that we can
see what that means. Let's just go to
the whiff here. We're just interested in
the animation.
Anyway, we can see that it loops through
the entire thing and uses that as its
modulation output. Basically, the height
of the graph here. Now, this curve is
fully editable. There's several
different ways that you can add it by
just double clicking. You can add
different points and you can move them
around. You can also again set up the
curvature to make different paths here.
You can see that there's a little grid
being displayed. So if you hold shift,
you're going to be able to make steps in
that grid size. Also, if you want to
ever sync to the grid, you can just hold
alt. So now holding alt, you can see
that all of the points are synced to the
grid if I move them around. And the same
will be true if I hold both alt and
shift. Then I'm able to make the steps
so that they're synced to the grid. Now,
if you're not a fan of holding shift,
you can also just select the same tool
over here. And then again, you're able
to make these kind of steps, but you're
also able to make these kind of shapes
where you're able to make triangles up
or ramps up and ramps down. And the grid
itself can be controlled over here where
we can both set the vertical grid as
well as the horizontal grid. There's
some more editing modes as well. If
we're back in here, what we can do is we
can select multiple points by just
dragging around them and then moving
them together. This is going to maintain
the relative space between the points.
But if you don't want to do that, if you
want to actually stretch up the relative
space, you can do that as well. You just
hold control and then drag on any of
these points. As you can see, rainbow
colors will appear on the other points.
And that is how you're selecting them.
All of the points that are colored are
going to be selected in this. And now if
I move this around, you can see that we
have stretching available here. And
depending on how far you're setting the
control, it is going to be stronger and
weaker. If I move it further, you can
see that I can now move the whole space.
Now, all of these shortcuts do work in
all of the other graphs that we have
seen up until this point. like for
example the spectral filter graph, the
warp mode remap graph or the distortion
X shaper graph. Something that doesn't
work in other graphs but is really cool
in the LFO to do is the modulation of
points. If I drag over a macro, you can
see an X or a Y opens up and I can
actually modulate that. So now moving
this
around will move around the point. Of
course within the restriction that it
cannot cross over in other points
because you can never have two values at
the same time for a graph. The same is
going to be true for these curves. So
you can modulate this curve over here
just like that. And it's going to go up
and
down. By the way, this is also possible
for the envelopes. So again, for the
envelope curvature, you can actually
modulate
that. Finally, in regards to editing
your graphs, the final thing that I want
to show is this pop out window where you
can edit in more detail. You're going to
have the same grid options over here,
but what you also see are going to be
the playback options as well as being
able to load and save custom curves. So
again, there's going to be different
presets available over here. You can
also generate random curves like this
curved version or this flat version. And
as you can see, you can also take the
shape from any of the oscillators. So
now we have the shape from wave table B
here, which is just a saw wave. If I
make a little bit more of
a different wave table, like a more
complex
one. Let's see if I can find something
interesting. Say this shape over here.
If I now go and go over here, oscillator
B, we actually get that shape in the
LFO. So, as you can see, these playback
options and saving options are also
present below over here. When it comes
to the playback, you have forward
reverse playback. So, it's going to go
in reverse like
this. And then we have our ping pong,
which means that it's going back and
forth. There's a few more playback
options, mainly the free re-trigger and
envelope modes over here. This means
that it's not going to re-trigger any
time that a new note is playing. So, it
will just start working and it will
continuously loop. This will re-trigger
the sound every time that a new note is
played. and so will envelope mode, but
envelope mode allows you to just play
through the shape once. Meaning that
this can act as an envelope as well,
like this, but with a more custom
shape. Right now, it's set to ping-pong,
but if you just set it to forward, it
will only go forwards once. And of
course, reverse, it will only go reverse
once. The parameter below that is the
mono parameter, which means that if you
turn this on, the LFO will actually be
singular for all of the individual
voices. Whereas if it's turned off, a
new LFO will be generated for every
voice that the synthesizer plays,
meaning that there can be slight
differences of the LFOs in individual
voices. Below that, we have the
anchoring option, which ties the LFO to
the door playback. So that means that if
you set it to free running, this will
always make sure that it's in line with
the DAW. And if you turn it off,
specifically if you're changing and
modulating around like time values over
here, then you have a chance to actually
go out of sync with the project itself.
So anchoring timing in place will make
sure that you're always in sync. But
that does mean that sometimes you're
going to get clicks in your modulation
as it snaps from one position to the
other in the LFO. Next to that, we have
our timing options. Again, we're going
to have a rate here, which is going to
determine how fast the LFO is playing,
which we can set both in time signature
as well as in hertz. When it comes to
time signature, you have access to
triplet mode, which is going to give you
triplet options as well as dotted
options. We have this rice option over
here, which is going to determine how
long it's going to take for this LFO to
get to a full strength of modulation. So
that means that for every time the note
re-triggers, it is going to slowly rise
up over the duration that we set over
here. And then if we want to properly
like actually delay the starting of the
LFO, we can do that here. So this will
literally delay the LFO from starting
after the note trigger by whatever
amount that you set here. Now we do have
some really jagged edges which can
sometimes be a problem. So there's also
LFO smoothing. This is going to smooth
out any of the modulation and you can
see that in the graph as well what the
resulting modulation will actually look
like. Finally, we have the phase of the
LFO, which is going to determine the
starting position. So, if I set the
phase to say over here and we set it in
free mode, you will see it's starting
from
there. Let's set it to
[Music]
re-trigger. And now, you can see it's
starting every time from the same
position. Now, this is just going to be
the most basic of LFOs. This is just
going to give you an individual
modulation value that you can assign
anywhere. But let's say that you want to
have two modulations values for every
LFO. That is where the puff LFO comes
in. As you can see, I'm setting
different modes here. I did not want to
overwhelm you directly with all of the
different modes. So, I'm introducing
them now. Like, I was hoping to create
the effect of you thinking, okay, we're
done with the LFO. We're moving on now.
But no, there's like four more different
modes. It's always more complex than you
think it is with this synth. So, the way
that the path graph works is that you
again can create points. So, I'm
creating one, two, three, four. As you
can see, I'm creating this closed graph.
And we can just set up points like this
curve between them. Some curves are
going to be very strong depending on how
far away they are from each other. You
can also see that they're of course
restricted. So if you go here and I set
this curvature all the way there, it's
just going to result in a flat line. And
that is because we can now use X and Y
values. So the X value and the Y value
to modulate different parameters. And
what is going to happen is that there's
going to be a point that is going to be
moving around this line and moving in
circles.
So, let's set this a little bit slower
so that you can
see. Seems that we have an extra point
there. So, that is why it was stopping
there. What seems to be interesting is
that if you have more points here, it is
going to spend more time here.
So I guess that is kind of a cool way to
speed up and slow down different parts
of the modulation. Right now though we
have a closed loop. So that is maybe not
what we want. We can also have an open
loop. So as you can see the last point
is disconnected. That actually means
that it's actually going to jump the gap
here. So you can have discontinuous
modulations if you want to. So, let's
just move
this all over here so that you can
see it just jumps over. And if you
actually wanted to have it kind of go
back and forth, you can do that by just
setting this to ping pong again.
Again, modulation points can also be
modulated themselves. So, we can set the
X value here, can change the Y value,
and we can change curvatures, and all
that is going to
[Music]
work. So, one thing that will be really
interesting is using one path as your
main modulation source and then going in
with other LFOs and setting up different
custom shapes or stuff like that and
then modulating a whole bunch of
different points. That way, your main
modulation is going to be this kind of
constantly changing and morphing entity
as opposed to just like a standard
default shape. And that is literally
just going to get you one extra layer of
modulation and therefore an extra layer
of complexity. The next three types are
going to be random generators. So, we
have a Loren attractor here. This is
going to generate chaos in two
dimensions. As you can see, still an X
and a Y. And what you'll see is that
it's just going to be following these
paths that are displayed here.
Sometimes it likes to hover around
certain
[Music]
area, but it's basically just generating
these semi- random paths around these
predictable shapes here. And the same is
going to be true for the rustler here,
but that is just going to have like one
point and it's going to be circling
around
[Music]
that. The final type is going to be a
one-dimensional randomizer. Again, as
you can see, no X and Y here. And this
is going to be our sample and hold. So,
this is going to generate like infinite
step sequences.
Probably really cool to put something
like this on a
[Music]
filter. Now, as you can see, the LFOs
have gotten a massive upgrade from
version one. They're actually replacing
the chaos oscillators that were in the
global tab. So, chaos oscillator one is
going to be this Lorettes here, and
chaos oscillator 2 is going to be this
roster here. And of course, you can have
as many of those as you want of each of
them. So let's say that you want two of
the first one. You can set two Lorettes
here and one Rossler. And instead of
being limited to just one of each type,
you're going to have as many as you want
available. What hasn't been upgraded
though is the velocity and the note.
This is still pretty much the same as it
was in Serum 1 where we just have
velocity input which we can remap. So
again, just like any other remap graph,
all of the input velocities are going to
lie on this axis and then you can output
them to whatever other value that you
want on the Y-axis. So that means that
all of the velocity information is going
to come in here is going to be remapped
by this map and then you can apply it to
whatever parameter that you want. Most
likely it's going to be something like a
volume or maybe a filter cutff. And then
we also have the note value which is
literally just going to be the note in
[Music]
pitch. Some really cool sounds there by
the way. And then the final modulator
that you're going to be able to access
on this main page here is the mod wheel,
which we can see over here. This is
basically similar to a macro in that it
just goes up and down and you can assign
multiple parameters to have them do the
same
thing. Our phaser is going a little bit
crazy, but you get what I'm doing here.
The difference is is that most of the
keyboards actually come with a mod
wheel. In fact, if I go over here, this
would be a mod wheel. And just for
continuity sake, it is going to be
really easy for you to map the mod wheel
to presets in a way that you would also
use the mod wheel on your media
controller so that it's like a onetoone
representation. But other than that, it
is not different in functionality from a
macro in that it's just one parameter
which you turn up or down to actually
change the value. Now, for all of the
other modulators, we're actually going
to have to move over to the matrix
screen, which means that it's probably a
good idea that I explain this first.
This is going to be an overview of all
of the modulations that are being
applied in the patch. So each individual
modulation that we have now assigned
over here is going to get its own entry,
its own row in this table. And this is
where you can tweak the finer details of
your modulations. Now starting from the
top, there's a button to actually expand
this so that you don't see the
modulators and you have a bigger list
here. We then have the ability to
reorder the table. So we're just able to
drag these around and order them however
we want. On the right here, we can also
order them in other ways. So we can sort
either by the source or by the
destination, which are going to be the
source over here and the destination
over here. We're then able to lock the
entire mod matrix like we are with many
other parts of the syn and then start
browsing presets to hear what different
preset sounds like with the same
modulation assignments. We then have two
options to create two basic modulations.
A verbat effect which uses an unused LFO
and it assigns the mod wheel to create
the verb amount. And then we have the
velocity to amp assignment meaning that
your patch is going to be velocity
sensitive. Finally, if you wanted to
delete all of the macros from the
modulation, all of these modulation
assignments here, you can do that really
quickly with this button over here,
which as you can see clears all of the
macros. Now, diving deeper into the
matrix itself, what we can do is we can
set our sources here. So, we can just
find any source that we want. We have
our envelopes, LFOs, we have some note
information. We have actual oscillators.
So, we can take any of the output from
any of the oscillators and use that as
our modulation source. We can find the
macros over here. So, that's these
macros. We have MP control which is note
expression. Then we have the output of
the filters. So the same thing that
applied to the oscillators, we can also
take the output from the filter and use
it to modulate any parameter. And then
we have some other miscellaneous over
here. The ones in the note that we have
to go through is basically everything
except the note and velocity which are
going to be this note and velocity here.
The modulation sources that we haven't
seen yet are going to be the active
voices here which is the total amount of
voices that are able to be played
divided by the amount of voices that are
actually playing. So you're going to
kind of get a ratio of how many voices
you're playing with the syn and that
usually translates to how many notes of
the total amount of notes that you're
accepted to play. Again later all of the
voice stuff is going to make more sense
when we actually talk about that. We
have these note on parameters here.
First two are going to be the alt. These
are going to generate alternating
sequences of zero and one. So like zero
modulation and maximum modulation. And
alt 2 is just going to be the inverse of
alt 1. So if alt one is generating one
then alt two will be generating a zero
and vice versa. We have the
randomization for each of the node. We
have two randomizations that are going
to send the same value to multiple
different destinations. And then we have
this discrete one which is going to send
each destination that it's assigned to a
different random value. Now I talked
about velocity before but we also have
release velocity. Normally velocity
refers to how hard you press down a
note. And then release velocity is going
to determine how hard you release a note
or how quickly you release a note I
should say. And then the last three
modulation sources in this list is going
to be voice index and voice mod one and
two. This is going to be making more
sense once again when we talk about
voices, but this is actually going to be
a different voice than the other voices
that I was talking about. It will all
make sense later, I promise. Now, the
other ones that are in here, we've
already seen the mod wheel, but we also
have the after touch. Theoretically,
velocity is a one-time thing in the
sense that you press the note and that
is going to have a certain speed to it,
how fast you press it. But you can
always kind of even if you have the note
already pressed, press down a little bit
more
like I can always touch more, right? And
there are some devices that can actually
read this touch and in that case you can
use this extra touching as another
modulation source, this extra pressure
on the key. The same is going to be true
for polyonic after touch, but it's going
to be changing for every note. So every
note that you're playing is going to
have its own pressure that you can
actually determine and use as a
modulation source for that particular
note. Then we have the pitch band, which
is going to be this pitch band over
here. Again, pitch wheels are going to
be very common in all kinds of different
sins and keyboards and whatnot. And
again, mine has also one. It's going to
be the furthest out one over here. This
is the one that snaps back to the center
as well.
I don't know how well that will show on
camera, but that is because it will
always stay in the middle. Because if
you go down with the pitch, it is going
to pitch down. And if you go up with the
pitch, it is going to pitch up. And that
behavior is also replicated in here. So
if I move this down and release, it
snaps back to the middle quickly. So
that it's completely out of the way, I'm
going to cover the rest of the pitch,
which really is just two parameters. The
amount of pitch that is being raised or
lowered when you go higher. So you can
go both negative and positive 24 here.
And here as well, you can go negative
and positive 24 to determine the pitch
bend when you go to the lower part. So
what could be really cool, for example,
is if you want to go an octave up, you
move the pitch down. And if you want to
go two octaves up, you move the pitch
[Music]
up. And a cool thing about the pitch is,
as you can hear, it's going to be
completely smooth. So you can do really
cool smooth pitch bands. Now the final
modulation source that we have to look
at is this fixed one over here. This is
just going to output a fixed value
whatever the maximum value of this
modulation assignment that you have is.
So as you can see this is where you set
the modulation amount. This is going to
be equivalent to going into any
modulation say this level over here and
actually dragging on this parameter
handle. So this will actually update in
here as well if we find that exact
modulation which I believe is this one.
So moving this around we will go back
and we can see that it's back up again.
Go down we can see that it's lower
again. Now, if you would like to change
how the amount is actually reflected,
you can do that with the remap mod. So,
to show this example, what I think is
good is that I quickly go and initialize
here. And I'm just going to set up a
macro for the level so that we have a
very basic modulation, which is just a
full amount. Let's quickly look at this
curve over here. What I can do first of
all is just go up and down and kind of
bend it. What this is going to do is
it's going to make sure that the
modulation is more active towards either
the top or the lower part. So let's set
it to the top and let's just see what
happens to like the speed of how fast
this goes up into higher
values. Even this low, it is already at
almost the maximum of this parameter
here.
And if I go the other way around, it is
actually going to stay at lower values
more. Now, this was how it used to be in
Serum 1 that you can just move this up
and down. But now, if you double click,
you can actually edit this curve. And I
could, for example, have it go up at the
halfway point of the modulation and then
down
again. In this case, there's an extra
point here, which I then also have to
move down.
And you can probably guess that it is
really powerful to have, for example, a
macro control multiple different
parameters and then still have
differences in the way that that
modulation is applied to the different
parameters. Again, with just like all of
the other curves that we have seen,
there's presets available. So, you have
a whole bunch of factory presets. We
have a few remapping presets here which
are doing something special apparently.
And you can save your own shapes which
will then show up here as well. We also
have smoothing in this case specifically
for the rice and full. So, we can unlink
those and have them different. The rise
is going to go how fast is the
modulation going to go up and the follow
is going to determine how fast is the
modulation going to go down. So now if I
go like this, if I turn it all the way
up, we should see it being smoothed a
lot more.
[Music]
And we can see that it's taking a while
for it to go from the actual position
that I set because of the amount of full
that I've set and of course also the
rise. So it's like literally just
smoothing and making the whole thing
work slower. And maybe to quickly show
you how powerful the modulation system
is within Serum in terms of just the
amount of parameters that you can change
about the sound. Even the rise and fall
of these modulation curves are in and of
themselves parameters that you can
modulate. So now we can see that macro 5
is actually assigned to modulation one
smoon up which is this parameter over
here. This actually smoons the
modulation going up as I said. So that
means that almost all of the parameters
that you're going to see are going to be
able to be modulated by zero. One thing
that you cannot modulate though is this
amount itself here. If I take a macro
and I drag it on there, you can see that
that isn't really working. The way that
you're going to be able to do that is
through the aux source. So this is where
we set up an auxiliary modulation that
is going to be multiplied with this
modulation here. I've now set the same
modulation. So that's not going to work.
Let's set macro 2. So now this
modulation isn't going to do anything
unless macro 2 is turned up all the way.
So now the modulation is going to
[Music]
work. With it down, it does
nothing. And if we set macro 2 halfway,
the modulation amount is going to be
scaled by half.
So this is literally just like a
multiplier for this amount over here.
Now right now the modulation is working
in one direction. So right now the
parameter is set all the way down and
the modulation is just moving it this
way. But sometimes in modulations it is
useful to have it go both ways for
example with the panning or with pitch
tuning or something like that. If you
want to be able to tune both up and down
with modulation and you want 50% to be
the original tuning without any of the
modulation. Then in that case, let's say
that we go in here and we take macro 8
and we want to assign that to the pitch.
We can also show how that works in here
where you select some of your
parameters. You just have lists with all
of the different parameters. And usually
what I find really really annoying is to
find the exact parameter that I need. So
what I like to do instead is usually go
to the parameter that I want and then
just assign a dummy modulation and then
go in here and change the modulation to
whatever I need. And you can already see
that right now this is set to biparter.
So it automatically goes and takes this
modulation and makes it bipolar. We can
see that this is the center position.
And here it goes to the right and the
left. And that is being controlled by
this switch over here. So we go bipolar,
uniolar, bipolar, uniolar. To the right
of the destination, we have our little
output monitoring. So this is showing
you exactly what the modulation is doing
on the parameter. It is actually showing
you the output of the parameter I
believe. So it will sum multiple
modulations together. We can again test
that by initializing and for example
taking the level here making sure that
we have a time modulation happening on
it and then let's also assign a macro.
So if the macro is turned up it is
always going to be fully up and the
parameter cannot go any further. So that
means that even in the LFO we should see
the
output stay all the way up. So this is
actually an output of the parameter
value not the individual modulation
value. Now, I've talked about the aux
source before, but there's a few extra
things that we want to show here. So,
let's set up another ox source macro 2
here. And what we can do is we can
invert its behavior. So, now at the
bottom, it is going to be fully
modulating. And at the top, it is going
to be fully not
modulating. And still in between, it's
going to be a percentage of
both. We can again remap this whole
thing. So, we again have a curve here,
which you can also click on to edit.
instead of just simply inverting it, it
will actually be remapped by this thing
in the same way that the modulation
itself is remapped here. This remapping
will just be applied to the actual
modulation amount here. Then finally, we
have our output. So this is going to be
another multiplier. So let's say that we
set this up back to normal by just
deleting some of these points here,
there and there. Double clicking deletes
them. Let's say that we still want this
to go to 0% and we don't have macro 2
here or we're using it for something
else. So, we cannot actually use a macro
here. What we can do if we want this to
be outputed at 50% is just set its
output to
50 and it's still just going to go
halfway. Finally, the final knob here is
the temporary bypass. So, you can just
bypass any modulation that you have so
that it's not going to apply without
actually deleting it. Or you can just
fully delete it by clicking over here.
Now, one of the interesting things about
Serum is that it's one of the first sins
that I know of that has true audio rate
modulation from the actual oscillators.
So we have seen that we can use the
oscillators as well as like filter
signals and that stuff to modulate
parameters but that is actually
happening at audio rate. So whatever you
expect to happen is actually going to
happen within the synth when you do
audio rate modulation. A lot of other
sins kind of go around it and and kind
of simulate it and and don't really do
it because it is just really hard to
implement audio rate modulation. But
Serum has been able to do that. And that
is really, really powerful, especially
if you think about how many different
parameters you're actually able to
modulate. And as I said before, it is
basically just everything that you see
on the screen is modulatable. Like
there's very few parameters that you
cannot just modulate in these main
screens in like the mixer, in the
effects, all of the different, you know,
effects parameters and whatnot. There's
going to be very little that you cannot
modulate. The final tab that we haven't
seen yet is the global step. there's
some interesting thing going on. But
over here, you're going to have your
main settings. These are usually not
stored with the preset. So, these are
going to be your own personal settings.
And this is just going to determine how
the plug-in actually behaves and
whatnot. It includes things like, okay,
how it's going to work. If you double
click on a parameter, is that going to
allow you to type a value or reset the
parameter. You have the tool tips. You
have parameter value tool tips and that
kind of stuff. Mouse wheel control if
you want that. You're going to find some
MP settings over here and then some
other settings as well. Right next to
that we have the voice control area.
This is where you can randomize some
parameters between note presses. And
this is where what we saw before in the
modulation matrix. This voice index and
voice mod one and two is going to come
in. We can see mod one and two over
here. So you can literally just set this
set up some values over time and it's
going to use that as a modulation. So
now if I go into the matrix setup
uh
note voice mod one here and I set that
to the level of oscillator A. If we go
through this, we can see that every note
that I press, we're going to get a
different
value. And as you can probably already
hear, it is actually circling through
all of these values here.
We can also randomize some of the
parameters. So there's four different
parameters here like the panning. We
have the D-tune amount. We have the
filter cutff for each voice. And then
finally, we have different envelope
parameters. So it's going to change some
of the timings on the envelopes. You can
see that there's scaling percentages for
stuff like that down here as well. And
of course, you can always set individual
values if you want to as well. Now,
let's say that there's an oscillator
that you don't want to apply this effect
to, but some other oscillators you do
want to do that. can always select which
oscillator it is being applied to here.
And again, there's going to be presets
available for this stuff, as well as you
being able to save your own presets.
Next to the voice control, we have our
quality settings. This is where you're
going to determine how high quality the
syn is going to play. Usually, it's
already going to be a good quality. As
you can see, the lowest possible quality
is good quality cuz there isn't a bad
quality in the synth. Like, it's not
just all of a sudden going to sound
terrible at the lowest quality. But what
is going to happen is that you're
probably going to get more accurate high
frequencies at ultra than you're going
to get at good. So if you're doing a lot
of crazy stuff and you're generating a
lot of high frequencies, then this is a
setting that you may want to check out
to get a more accurate representation of
your high frequencies. We have the Serum
1 compatibility mode and this will allow
you to use the Serum 1 engine
faithfully. So any Serum 1 preset that
you load up will sound exactly the same.
There are some slight differences
between like the actual sound engine and
you're able to change that with this
setting over here so that presets sound
the exact same if they happen to not
sound the exact same. And then finally,
we have smoothing here which I believe
applies to stuff like automations. So
when you have an automation in your DAW
and you're just going to go like this
and then suddenly snap from one value to
the other, I believe a slight bit of
smoothing is applied to that. And I
believe that this is what this is
referencing to. The other types of
smoothing that I could think of is stuff
like the LFO smoothing and some of the
the smoothing that we've seen in some of
the filters and modulation sources and
whatnot, but I believe that this is
referring to the automation smoothing
that I talked about before. Finally,
below the quality settings, we have the
tuning. This is where you can load
alternative tuning files if you're
interested in something like a tonal
music or just using a different set of
tuning rules. Specifically, if you're
making non-western music, this is very
useful because it allows Serum to just
make sounds for whatever tuning system
that you're using. And then the very
final piece of information that you're
going to see on this screen is going to
be your build and the date of the build
together with like some numbers behind
it so that it's easy to identify if you
ever want to report a bug or something
like that. This is where you find this
information which is crucial for
something like bug reporting or seeing
if presets are compatible with the
version of Serum that you have
installed. The next area that I want to
focus on is going to be the lower bar.
So that is going to be this lower area
over here. This is where you're going to
find all of the playing settings. So the
way that notes are treated before sound
is actually generated and that kind of
stuff. We've already talked about the
pitch went and the modulation wheel. But
now let's look at the clip setting. If I
click on here, you have your whole DAW
open and you can actually just write
music in here. Yes, it is this crazy.
This is like an actual like clip
launcher MIDI editor thing. So by
default this is disabled but if you
enable it over here what is going to
happen is it's going to take 12 notes
and it allows you to play 12 different
clips you can select which of the
octaves it is going to use over here. So
by default it's going to be the minus2
octave which is going to be the very
lowest octave that your DAW is going to
support so that it doesn't get in the
way of you actually like writing
melodies and whatnot. And one of the
really cool things that you can
therefore do is you can write in say
your chords or your backing maybe
arpeggio or whatever in the individual
clips and then you can play over a
melody a couple of octaves higher and
then still with the same media
controller like switch between different
arpeggio or chord settings. So starting
off at the top left we have access to
the macros here if you want to use macro
control on any of the parameters that we
see over here. Again a lot of this stuff
can actually be like modulated and
whatnot.
This one over here seems to be
modulatable. I thought that these ones
would be as well, but at least the rate
is. Right below that button, we have our
global settings where again, you're
going to be able to find preset banks.
This case, I don't believe or there are
some chords in here. We have some drums,
some guitar voicings, and that's it.
Right below the preset area, we have the
setting which determines if multiple
clips can play at the same time. So, if
you want that, you set it to poly,
otherwise you set it to mono. And then
we also have this edit all option which
allows you to edit all of the individual
clips at the same time. So if you want
to set for example a common length or
something like that and this is an easy
way to do that. You set it to edit all
set the length that you want and then
you turn it off again so that you can
start editing individual ones again.
That brings us to our individual clip
settings which we can scroll through
like this. So here we have like presets
and whatnot for individual clips as
opposed to like whole banks of clips
which we find over here. Below that as I
said we have the length and then we have
this KB span here. This is going to
determine how it's going to react to
incoming MIDI nodes. So both mono and
poly are going to transpose the notes by
incoming MIDI nodes. And then offset
mode is actually going to change the
starting position depending on an
internal parameter which is called if I
hover over here this offset quantize
setting. And this setting is going to be
available in the modulation matrix. I
believe it's this clip player offset. So
you can kind of modulate the starting
position of the clip. I believe it is
both possible to do that globally as
well as with each individual clip. So if
I go back here, we
have the global offset here and then we
have individual clip offsets. We have
this transposition parameter over here
if you want to pitch it up or down. So
this is literally just going to pitch up
and down the notes that we see in here.
We have our playback modes. Again,
there's a whole range of different ways
that it's playing through it. if it's
going to start and just kind of loop
like this or if it's going to reverse,
if it's going to go back and forth, it's
it's going to play it like a oneshot.
You can see that there's also like
random play options over here. So, you
definitely have to experiment to really
get a feel for what it's doing. And then
some of these options like for example
the random have this extra time
parameter which you can set over here
which is going to determine of course
how this randomization is actually going
to work. After that, we have a rate
multiplier. So it's going to take this
length and just multiply it so that the
playback speed is for example it plays
twice in this length
[Music]
here. And you can also unsync that if
you want to just do that and have it
[Music]
play. So you can play like melodies that
are like speeding up and slowing down
and whatnot. We have this launch
quantise option over here which is going
to determine where like within the
project it is going to fall. So whenever
you trigger a note, say slightly after
the 16 note has just played, it is going
to wait to the next 16 note or the next
eighth note or the next 32 note,
whatever you set up in terms of note
length, it is going to wait until the
next one until it starts to trigger so
that you can quantize it with your
actual project tempo. We have re-trigger
options, whether it re-triggers upon
incoming notes. So if you play the same
note to trigger a clip
twice, it is going to re-trigger
here. And without it, of
course, it's going to continue. We have
the note gate, which allows you to turn
it off and on the with the note
itself. And then finally, we have
velocity triggering over here, which is
going to determine whether these
velocities that you're able to set in
here are going to be multiplied with the
actual velocity coming in. Below that,
we have the menu for recording. So any
incoming MIDI notes will be recorded
into the clip that you're recording
into. And you can either replace the
current information there or just add to
it. If you want to add extra notes or
extra like iterations of notes on top of
each other, you can do that. And it
comes with this handy option here for a
metronome. So if you want to play to a
metronome when you're playing this in,
you can do that as well. Now having a
look into the actual editor, this is
where you're going to be either playing
in or laying down your MIDI notes.
Again, double click to just lay out a
med note. And then it's going to act
basically like a piano roll. You can see
that by default it snaps to whatever
note length that you have set over here
which we can either like double or half
right double the grid or half the grid
like this or we can set up a triplet
grits if we want to. So if we want to
play in triplet notes we can do that as
well. One two three triplet
notes. What we can also do is rightclick
disable the snap and then we can just
draw in notes however we want. This is
really cool if you want to do some
a-hythmical kind of music. And then the
final option is this auto adjustable
grid here. So if I then start to zoom
in, you can see that the grid keeps
updating and becoming smaller and
smaller. And you can see that reflected
over here as well. So if I zoom out, you
can see that number updating. Uh we'll
turn off triplets here for now. You can
also see that it works without triplets.
Here below we have the velocity which
you can set however you want. We also
can add other parameters here like the
attributes of certain notes like the
chance that it gets played. For example,
we can make it so that this note over
here and here and this one has a lower
chance of playing. We can add individual
expressions here. We can add individual
macro settings. We can add a whole bunch
of medcc information. And then finally,
we have some global settings like
transpose and the key and the scale
here. These are going to be updating
these individual parameters here which
we'll talk about later. Now, all of this
is really, really powerful in
combination with a very surprising fact,
and that is that Serum is now also a
MIDI generator. So, you can actually
send this MIDI out to whatever other
device that you want, either just the
clip player or the clip player and the
arpeggiator. The arpeggiator is this
other thing over here, which is this
little thing. But you'll find its output
is going to be over here. So, if you set
it to on, both the clip as well as the
arpeggiator is going to be sent. Or if
you just want to send the clip layer,
that is also possible. The final thing
that I should show in here is that you
have access to actual note expressions
as well. So we can do that per node
pitchband thing that it's very commonly
known for. You can just set up whatever
pitchbend that you want. Even if we have
like a chord in here, say that we have,
I don't know, a chord like this where we
have three notes and we have a chord
like this with three notes and we want
that to pitch from here to here. We can
do that. So starting with the re-trigger
here, let's hear how that sounds.
can see some of the chances working here
as well. Some of times the notes don't
get played and sometimes they do. There
is, by the way, a little bit of an
output which actually shows you exactly
what is being played here. So if you're
not entirely certain and you're doing
for example a lot of stuff with chance
where you've set different chances for
different notes and it becomes really
unrecognizable what the actual pattern
is then this is an easy way to see what
is actually
[Music]
happening. Now, let's say that you have
this MIDI clip and you're happy with it,
but you want to extend it a little bit.
You can do that by going over here. So,
this extends the med clip and you can
make it longer. And now you can see that
it's updated there. You can also set a
different starting position if you want
to. And again, you can see that the
length is updated, but now we have a
different starting position. So, all of
this stuff is stored over here, but it
doesn't actually get played. When it
comes to zooming, you can zoom in and
out here by scrolling. And you can
scroll up and down over here. I believe
if you hold control, yes, it will also
zoom over here. And then holding shift
allows you to scroll back and forth like
this when you're zoomed in. If you want
to zoom in vertically, like just showing
fewer notes on the screen, I guess you
can do that like this. Of course, you
can also show much more notes. So, this
is usually useful if you want like a
full overview and you're doing many
different stacks or many different
octaves or just some very large ranges
in whatever way that you're doing it.
I'm saying whatever way that you're
doing it because you can imagine that
with something like a multi-sampler full
of drums. It can be the case that you're
not really playing octaves of the same
instrument. You're just playing very
large ranges because some of the drums
are very low on the keys and some of the
drums are very high on the keys that
they're like assigned to. So it doesn't
necessarily have to be octaves, but it
can be that sometimes a range is like
very big and then you want to zoom out a
little bit. You can do that by holding
alt and of course you can also zoom back
in. So I believe that was the clip
manager. Honestly, this was a little bit
the hardest part for Serum to
understand. One, because it is not the
workflow that I'm usually used to, and
two, because this is something that is
completely new in Serum 2. Like, a lot
of the other features are kind of
extensions of features that were already
there. And then, of course, that means
that there are also features that I have
already started playing with like over
10 years ago. So, that means that when
it comes to the clip launcher, I don't
know if I have set everything. I do want
to quickly talk about three new knobs
that I haven't covered because I forgot
that they were in the script, but these
are the three knobs over here. One is so
that you can hear selected notes. Turn
this off. No note will play if I'm
drawing stuff in. If I turn it on, you
will get a little
preview. This case, we're modulating the
volume in a way. So sometimes it doesn't
play. We have the fold here. This allows
you to see only the notes that you're
already playing. This is very useful if
you're sequencing drums and you have all
of the drums that you want to use
selected. You can just hit fold and any
of the drums that you don't want to play
will not be shown. And then finally, if
you're zoomed in, so if I'm scrolling in
here, and you quickly want to zoom out
and see the whole thing, what you can do
is click over here, and this will zoom
out both horizontally and vertically in
a maximum amount of way, showing you all
of the notes that you have placed, but
nothing more. All right, so now I think
that we're truly through everything. And
if there is still something that I'm
missing, then please leave a comment
down below. But let's move on to the
arpeggiator. Again, this is going to be
a clip- based approach, which you're
going to be able to trigger with
different keys here. In this case, it is
set to minus one. So, this will be one
octave higher than the ones that you're
going to use for the clip here. It is
unfortunately not possible to trigger
both with the same. That would have been
really cool to be able to send the clips
from the clip here into the arpeggiator
and then have both different chords in
here like stacked up together with
different arpeggiators that then can be
applied on those chords in here. Now,
going through it, we have the global
settings again over here. So, this is
going to be a preset for all of the
different clips together. So, if you
want to just open up one preset that has
a whole bunch of different clips in
there, you can do that. But then also,
you have individual patterns, individual
shapes up here. These are not really
presets in the same way that these are
just like files stored on your PC
somewhere. These are still in the code,
like actually hardcoded. I'm not going
to describe what all of these things do.
Instead, what I'll do is I'll quickly
show this part of the manual so that you
can like see what the actual patterns
are because I found that that is much
easier than explaining kind of what
they're doing. So, there just going to
be a few patterns that are scrolling by
right now. And I'm really just talking
right now to fill up the space to make
sure that there isn't too little time
for you to actually see what is
happening with all of the different
patterns and whatnot. So, now that I've
given you enough time to actually
comprehend what all of the different
patterns are, let's go back into the
actual synth and continue watching what
is actually happening in the synth.
Because now that we're in the synth, we
do see that there's this one custom
pattern here which you can go in and
actually edit. So, you can write in your
own patterns. And this is again going to
work very similar to the clip launcher
here, but the way that this is going to
work is that it's going to divide up the
incoming notes that you already have. So
let's say that you have four notes
coming in from low to high, and you want
to play them in order from low to high.
You're going to write something 0 1 2 3.
So we're first going to play the lowest
notes, then one higher, then two higher,
then three higher. And I believe the way
that it's going to fill up all of the
notes that it uses for the patterns is
that it's going to start at zero, then
count up, and then count down. So if you
have seven notes in your chords, it's
actually going to start from minus one,
which means that you can write patterns
that become more complex and actually
have lower notes once you hit that seven
or eight note mark. Again, we have
velocity and a whole bunch of other
settings here for all of the different
notes that you're writing in. You can
also write in chords if you want to, so
you can layer multiple notes on top of
each other. We again have some playback
settings here on the left which are
going to be very similar to the ones
that we saw in the clip pattern because
again this is going to be very similar.
Again, it's also going to have like the
same grit and all of that kind of stuff.
So you'll see the same playback modes,
the same ones that require the time.
Here we do have this other thing which
is the step mode which will determine
how each step is played. So every step
is this thing over here. One step, one
step, one step. When you set this to new
only, it will only play the arpeggiator
once the chords are actually lining up
with the start of the arpeggiator that
you're playing. So, it's going to loop
around and if you start your chords at
the exact same time that it loops
around, then it's going to play the
arpeggiator and otherwise it isn't. And
chord means that instead of playing
individual steps, it will play the
chords that you're actually holding.
Then we have the warp setting that is
going to determine how repeats are
handled. Repeats is something that we'll
see over here, but these are basically
extensions of the pattern that you're
playing. Now, we left off in the pattern
window over here. And below that, we
have our timing settings. We've seen
this kind of setting before, so I'm not
going to explain it fully again. We have
our transpose setting here. This is
going to show you again the methods by
which it is going up or down. And the
way that this works, seeing that we have
the same thing over here and over here,
is that this is going to be for the
repeats. So this is going to take the
pattern that you already have and if
you're actually repeating it, it is
going to transpose differently between
different versions of that pattern.
Transpose in different ways dependent on
the shift and the range parameter. Here
we have the offset which allows you to,
as you can see with this pattern editor
open, move this line up and down, which
is your starting line. We have this
latch option over here which is going to
continue arpeggiating notes even if you
release the initial chords in input. And
then we have this through option which
is going to take your chords that you're
playing in input and also pass those
onto the actual synth instead of
actually removing those and replacing
them with the arpeggiator. The
arpeggiator is going to be layered on
top. We finally then have a note gate
here which is going to set the length of
all of the individual notes. So you can
see we have a full step here. If I set
the gate to 50, it will treat this note
as if it has half the length as it
currently has. And then finally here we
have a global probability so that you
don't have to go in here and set the
chance for each of the notes to say 50%,
if you want to have all of the notes
trigger at 50% chance. We have these
re-trigger options over here which
allows you to either re-trigger the
arpeggiators every time that you launch
a clip at a certain fixed rate or
depending on whether a note is being
pressed or not. So for every note it is
going to re-trigger or only for the
first note that you press in a group of
notes. And then finally here we have the
velocity control which is going to
determine what happens to the velocity
over the repeats of the arpeggiator. So
that is these repeats over here. And if
you turn this on, what you're able to do
is you're able to decay the velocity
over time. So you're able to set the
velocity target. And then with a decay
length, it is going to set how long it
will take for the velocity to kind of
over the course of the arpeggiator go to
this target. And again, this can be
re-triggered based upon incoming nodes
or not. Right next to the arpeggiator,
as we already talked about, we have a
general transpose. So, this allows
transpose the whole synth up or down.
And that's actually going to apply to
the incoming mini notes. So, if I go
like
this, keep in mind that this doesn't
update once a note is already
pressed. So, this really works on the
input. And what also works on the input
is both the key and the scale selection.
So you're able to select a key and then
the scale that you're working in to
restrict all of notes coming in input to
that scale and key. For that matter, you
also have the swing parameter over here
which allows you to slightly swing the
notes. So you can set up a swing timing
here. And then you can set in which
timing that swing is happening. Finally,
over here we have the oscillator
mapping. This is a little bit of a
different thing, but it allows you to
determine for which keys and velocities
which oscillators are going to play. So
let's say that for the highest keys we
don't want to have a sub oscillator. We
can restrict the sub oscillator to only
play for these lower octaves over here.
And then we don't want the noise to play
for the lowest velocity. So we set that
to say over here we want the arpeggiator
but only on our low velocity like chords
in the background not on our main leads.
So we're going to have the arpeggiator
only trigger for these lower notes over
here. And you can imagine that you can
really nicely divide up the synth
depending on exactly which notes need to
be able to play what and which
velocities need to be able to play what.
And that allows you to make the
instrument a little bit more dynamic
from a player perspective as it's
actually going to interact more to what
you're doing in terms of playing
different keys and different velocities.
And this will also be the way that
you're able to create those standard
kind of split presets where one half of
the preset is, for example, doing a bass
patch and the other half is doing a lead
patch. And you're able to play both with
both of your hands and have a lead on
your right hand and a bass on the left
hand. By just setting up, for example,
say that we set up something like this,
we can now make oscillator B responsible
for the bass patch and oscillator A
responsible for the lead patch. And of
course, because of Serum's architecture,
that means that they can both have
separated filters now, that they can
both have separated effects now. And
that they can sum together and then be
processed together as well. And that
allows you to basically have, as I said,
two different sounds in the same
synthesizer and play one with one hand
and one with the other and do all of
that within just one synth with this
oscillator mapping thing here. Now, the
final thing on the lower interface is
going to be the voicing and the
portimento settings. So, voicing, as I
alluded to before, has to do with both
the amount of notes that you're playing
and also somewhat like different
oscillators and different settings that
you're using. Right now, as you can see,
we have set the maximum polifany of
eight. And every note is just using one
voice. That is because of the particular
settings that we have. For example, if I
increase the D-tune voices, you can see
that that gets updated over here. And
then for every note that I play, a
certain amount of voices are going to be
used. I don't know why we're not getting
any outputs. Probably because of some
kind of modulation that is happening,
but that is okay. If you want to be able
to play just one voice at a time, you
can enable this mono setting over here.
So that is going to turn off the
polifany. And as you can see, we're only
able to play one voice at a time, either
zero or 14. Now, this is going to have
an effect mainly on the legato parameter
here. And that is determining how notes
interact with notes that are already
playing. So if I turn on legato, what's
going to happen just like we saw before
with the envelopes where we had its own
legato mode is that it's going to make
sure that all of the modulations that
are already in play are actually
maintained for the second note as
opposed to starting from the starting
position of all of the modulations. So
that means that if a modulation starts
here and then it starts to play for one
note and then over here a second note
triggers that second note will start
with the modulation all the way up and
then will continue in the same way. And
that is also true for the envelope and
all of the other modulations. Now let's
say that you want to make sure that
those notes are even more connected.
Let's say that we have mono and legato
turned on. What we can also do is add
some portimementoto. This is determining
whether you have a pitch glide between
notes. So if I do
this, let's turn off this filter so you
can hear
easy. It's kind of gliding between them.
You can turn this up to have more of an
effect like
that. If you want this effect to be
scaled towards the distance between the
notes, you can do that as well. So,
let's set this like
[Music]
this. It is going to move faster from
notes that are very distant from each
other than notes that are very close to
each other. So, that it's like nicely
scaled. And then finally, we have the
curvature over here which determines how
it is going to approach the new pitch.
So if you want it to go really quickly
to the new pitch, you set it up. If you
want it to hover below the new pitch or
at the old pitch, you just set it like
this. And then towards the end, it will
snap actually up to the new pitch.
Finally, if you want this effect to also
happen between notes, so if notes aren't
legato, then they're not going to have
this pitch snap
[Music]
effect. If you do want that to happen,
you can turn on the always and it will
still have this pitch gliding effect to
it.
[Music]
Now, there are some really, really
technical aspects of this whole playback
system. Specifically, how mono is
different from just setting polifany to
one. Like, you would assume that since
it's just giving zero out of 14 or 14
out of 14 when you're playing that this
would be the same as this, but it's like
internally technically not. And this can
have some effect on some really specific
situations, things that I cannot just
name or just show you by just
experimenting. But if the syn ever just
does like random playback behavior, if
there's anything that the syn does that
you cannot really explain, a good way to
see if you can rectify that is by just
turning off or on mono and like
switching between those and maybe one
polifany or even multiple polifany if
you're expecting to hear multiple notes
playing at the same time, of course. But
just the difference between being able
to play one note through the mono
setting versus being able to play one
note through the poly setting and
setting that to one. There is a
difference in some parts of ways that
the syn actually handles which again are
both very technical and very hard to
just kind of force and show. So this
might be one of the places that you have
to look when the synth is doing
something that you're not expecting. Now
at this point you may think that we're
pretty much done. We have covered the
whole interface after all. There are
still more things that I actually want
to talk about. And these are going to be
things that are going to be maybe a
little bit more hidden or just a very
small part in a certain space like the
next part that we're going to cover
which will be the wavetable editor which
you can find over here in the
oscillator. Here you can draw your own
wave tables or import and edit existing
ones. Keep in mind that you can also
directly import samples into the
oscillator if you don't want to edit it.
So I can go into any sample. you see the
same pattern in practice and just drop
it in here and see whichever one of the
import modes I like. Quickly going over
the import modes. There are three
different import modes that are dynamic
in pitch, meaning that they can follow
sounds that aren't necessarily at the
same pitch all the time. We also have
the pitch average, which is really
useful for stuff that stays on the same
pitch. Next up, we have the FFT, which
is going to import and do a spectral
treatment. So, it's going to do the same
thing as the spectral engine, but just
to create the wave tables. and different
window sizes are going to give you
different tonal results. And then of
course you can convert to any of the
other oscillators that take a normal
sample. But back in the wavetable
editor, you can also drag it in over
here and do the same thing. Let's just
import it as an FFT over here. And then
you can see that it imports and all of
the frames are here. Now at the top of
the wavetable editor, we're going to see
the harmonic editor. So that is this
stuff over here with all of these
individual bins. And then we have the
waveform representation down below. So
that means that you're going to be doing
your drawing mainly over here. And in
here, you're going to be editing
individual harmonics and their phases.
What's neat about this is that once you
start drawing, the harmonics update
automatically. If you don't want that to
happen, you can disable it over here.
And then above that, you can switch
between the different oscillators if you
ever need to. That way, you don't have
to like click out of the window, go in
here, turn on the oscillator, go in
here, and then start editing whatever
you need to edit. On the right side over
here, we have the zoom level. If I turn
the update on again and I do this, we
can see that we can actually zoom out
and into the harmonics if you want to
have closer editing. You can of course
also scroll through it over here, but
for some reason the scroll wheel doesn't
work in here. Now, also in harmonic
editor, you're going to see some
processes if you right click. So, first
of all, we have the ability to clear
things. First of all, we can clear
everything, which is just going to
result in silence for this wave cycle
for this individual table over here that
we're editing. Then, we can clear all of
the high frequencies or all of the low
frequencies. And this is going to depend
on where you select the area. So here we
see 30 to end and start to 30. And then
here we're going to see a different
number. For some reason it says zero,
which you can hover over it. And then
you can see the bin number. So if you
want to clear any certain frequency, you
can do that. The next process allows us
to generate saw wave harmonics. So it's
just going to generate us a saw wave
series. Right now we have the phases in
a different way. So it's not going to
look like a saw wave, but it is going to
sound like one.
Because of course the harmonic content
is going to be the exact same as always.
We have the ability to randomize
different bins. So we can do the low 16,
32 or 64 bins. And then we can also do
it with halves. That is because this
just is a randomization between on and
off. And here we also are able to
randomize between on and off and halves.
So you get these halves in between as
well. We can of course also randomize
all of the bins. So that is probably
going to result in some like very sharp
noise thing.
It's actually more coherence than I
thought it would be. But let's go back
to a saw wave to see what is going to
happen next because what we can also do
is generate random gaps. So, as you can
see, this is just going to like take out
certain areas. And what is actually
really cool is just doing what I just
did where you generate a saw wave and
then you just use a series like this.
And then with some other processes that
we will see later, you're able to
actually transfer this series of gaps
into other wavetables. Anyway, the next
process is going to be the progressive
fade. In order to show this, what I'm
going to do is I'm going to randomize
it. So now everything is randomized.
Going to do the same thing with the
phases. As you can see, we have the same
operations over here. So I'm going to do
the same with the phases over here. And
now we get this really like noisy
looking waveform. I'm quickly going to
go over here to normalize it. Again, I'm
going to explain these processes as well
later on. So I've just normalized it
like this. And now we can see we have a
very noisy mess also in the harmonics
here where it's just like random values
here. What the progressive fade is going
to do is it's going to bring it back to
a more natural sound. So if you ever
have a very noisy sound, you just
progressive fade. And now we normalize
it again. And now, as you can see, it
just progressively goes down in volume
over the harmonics, which is going to
result in a nice full
sound, as opposed to what we had before,
which was
this, which is way too sharp. The next
operation, what you can do is shifting
it up an octave. So, that is going to
shift every harmonic up an octave, and
you can also go down again. Finally, the
last operation to do is repeat bin
group. What that's going to do is it's
going to take all of the bins before the
position of the mouse where you select
it and it's going to just duplicate that
over indefinitely up until the end of
the harmonics. I'm again going to
normalize this so that you can see this.
But you get these kind of really nicely
shaped like spiky wave tables out of
this process. And you can maybe see the
repeating pattern showing up in here
where all of the volumes are a little
bit closer because again it's going to
have this kind of downwards progressive
fade to it so that it has a really like
nice tonality to it and it isn't too
sharp. The final options that we have
over here are toggleable. So you can
either draw even harmonics or odd
harmonics. Drawing the even harmonics is
going to look somewhat like this. So
you're just able to draw like that. And
then the same thing if you set it to odd
harmonics, you're able to just draw with
the odd harmonics in between. Finally,
you can snap the grid to quarters. Let
me quickly turn this off so that you can
see what happens here. This allows you
to just edit it in steps of quarters
like this. So you can fill in some
pretty cool looking almost digital kind
of slopes to it. It's almost like you're
making a geometry dash level. And then
finally what we're able to do because we
have this progressive fade to it. Let's
actually set that back. What we can do
is actually let's generate a saw wave
because we have this kind of progressive
fade to it. What we can do is we can
multiply the volumes of all of the bins
by their bin number. And that is going
to end up with our bins being equally
flat when we have a saw wave. And this
means that instead of having the
absolute volumes of each of the
harmonics, you're just editing kind of
how far the volume is away from the
default saw wave series, which is just a
little bit of a different way of
thinking about how to edit the
harmonics. Next up, for the face, you're
going to have the exact same processes
except for that scaling of the harmonics
with the volume because that doesn't
really make sense for the faces which
are measured in degrees. So, next up,
let's move on to this area over here.
This is where you're able to draw
different things. First of all, you have
the different brushes that you can
select. So, we saw before that you can
just select like a line brush here. We
can have a little sine wave in here if
we want to. We can have different
slopes, different smooth
slopes. We have little hills and troughs
here. And then we have
these kind of combining ways of drawing.
This seems to be just smoothing out what
you've already drawn. And here you can
smooth it out like this as well. So I
believe the play with these are that you
set up
whatever like complex shape that you
want and then you just go over it and
smooth it like this or like that. Of
course, when you're editing these
wavetables, always keep in mind that the
end loops back into the beginning. So
you don't want to have any like strong
clicks from here to here unless you're
making specifically a very clicky sound
there. That is something that you can do
because for example a square wave would
have the same kind of click that we see
over here also happening going back this
way to continue playing from here.
Anyway, the last brushes that we have is
this one over here. This just allows you
to move some height around like this.
And then we have this noise brush over
here. This just slowly increases the
kind of randomization, the kind of noise
in there. And this is going to get us
some very gritty sounds.
[Music]
Let's just try to smoothen this out a
little bit. See what the smoothening
does here. You get a nice smoothened
waveform. The final thing that I want to
show you is this option over here, which
actually mirrors this part of the wave
table over here. So you can kind of draw
into two separate ways. Seems to be a
little bit buggy when you're using the
smoothing tool. It doesn't seem to be
able to handle that. But as you can see,
this is an easy way of drawing in
symmetrical wavetables. Just quickly for
the wavetable nerds out there, there is
something really interesting going on
with the phases of these wavetables. So
as you can see we have this pattern over
here and then it goes into this three
three three and that continues for
almost the entire wave table and then at
the end we again get little extra bumps
here which is interesting. Oh yeah and
it also slightly skews upwards with the
phases here. You can see the zero phases
starting to creep up here and it just
goes up slightly more and more and more.
And to be honest, I have no idea what
that means, but that does look very,
very interesting. I wonder why it would
have this pattern in the middle and on
both sides, it would have this extra
little thing here. I wonder if that has
something to do inherently with the
symmetry or maybe some of the shapes
that we used within here. Either way,
that is the drawing section almost
complete. What is actually still very
important is the grid size. As you can
see, with the editing, everything is
dependent on the grid size. So being
able to set the grid size over here and
over here is really powerful to be able
to edit in more detail. What you can
also do is turn it all the way to zero
for both of them. And then you can just
free as you can see like this has some
really cool things that happen if you
cross over with the symmetry mode
on. Just a little dancing disco here.
Anyway, also with the grid size, what
you can do is you can turn it up a
little bit like this and this and then
move the wave cycle around like that and
like that. And here it also seems to
loop which can cause some interesting
variations like these kind of
variations. Now, one of the things that
you may have seen that has appeared is
this repeat button over here. This
allows you to repeat the last action
that you just did. In this case, that
was going down
here or not. Apparently, this is
switching the last action that you do on
here, which in my case was this, I
guess. So, what if I do shift octave up?
Then that repeats. Yeah.
Okay. Shift octave
down. Cool. Now, I've removed all the
high
frequencies. Now, there's still a lot
more that we can do with the wave
tables, which is mainly going to happen
in the process. Here there is a little
bit of an extra area where you can
import or export wavetables. Of course,
also anytime you have made a
modification to a wavetable if you go
down here, there's a save icon over here
where you can save it into your
wavetables. And if you do that, it is
going to show up in your user folder
over here. As you can see, I've added
extra folders in between recordings. And
if you ever need to access these folders
very quickly, one way to do that is go
into the Open Sphere 2 presets folder,
which is going to provide you with all
of the preset areas for all of the
different things that you can make
presets for, including the wave tables,
which you can see down below here. Keep
in mind that if you make modifications
to any of your files, you have to rescan
the disk. So, you have to rescan the
folders on this gear in order for those
things to show up in actual loaded
instances of zero. So, those are just
two of the ways that you can export your
wavetables. But before that, of course,
you have to process them. And that is
done over here. When it comes to
processes, this is where you're going to
be doing most of your fixing. This is
where you're going to be able to, for
example, normalize a frame. If it's not
normalized, if it's not loud enough, you
can remove any DC offset. It's not going
to apply over here. But let's say that
we just create some DEC offset. What we
can do is we can remove it. And then our
wave table is going to be neatly in the
middle. And then, of course, we can
normalize it. We can flip the wave table
both vertically as well as horizontally.
And then what we can also do is move the
wave table so that there's a zero
crossing lining up over here. Currently
that is not the case. As you can see,
this isn't at 0 dB. So this isn't at
silence, meaning that when it's going to
cycle, it potentially can cause clicks
and whatnot. And just in general, it is
good practice to have your wave tables
be at a zero crossing, which as you can
see currently is happening because it
goes from above here to below here. So
it's kind of cycling around. And in
doing so, right at this point where it
moves from one area to the other, it is
going to cycle from the top here to all
the way down here. Remember that there's
technically 48 samples, 24,48
measurement points making up this curve
here. So that movement is happening
really, really fast. And that is of
course why you cannot see some of the
movements in some of the pixels here
because there's just too much
information to show. Next up, we can set
a preset to initialize. So we set it to
silence. What we can also do is
crossfade it. So we can either fade the
edges. So this is going to fade to
silence, meaning that it's going to go
to here and here as you can
see. Or we can make sure that it
crossfades. This means that the
transition between the two areas is also
going to be smoother, but it's not
necessarily going to go to silence. Now
you may see that these depend on the
grid size together with the filter as
well. Here we are filtering. How this
works is that this isn't a clear
representation of any value. This is
just between the minimum and maximum.
And this is the value that you use to
control it. So if I set it higher and I
go to for example fade edges, it is
going to be sharper. And if I set it
lower, it is going to be stronger. So as
you can see now, we have a very strong
fade going on. And this is some cool
ways of creating extra like shapes in
it. There's almost like a saw wave shape
into it.
[Music]
Now what we can also do is some sample
reduction. So that is just going to down
sample the wave table. That looks like
that. And the final process over here is
sending it to the noise oscillator. So
now if we go into the oscillators, we
can see the actual shape being played
here. And now the noise oscillator is
actually going to play that back.
Let's quickly enable pitch tracking and
then turn up the pitch to say 48
semmitones so that it's at a high enough
pitch so that we can hear
[Music]
it. You can hear that those are the
exact same wave table. Now, so far all
of the processes that we have been doing
are on the individual frame. There are
also processes that happen on multiple
frames. I'm not going to go over the
individual frame. Once again, the first
ones that are new are the normalized. We
have already seen what it does, but you
can gain each one separately, or you can
just choose the maximum for all frames
and then use that as the gain. This next
option here allows you to remove the
fundamental frequency. So, that's just
going to remove the first harmonic of
every single wave cycle in here, meaning
that they're all going to lack a
fundamental. This is really nice if you
want to add a separate subbase. Say if
you're doing something like a dubset
base or something like that. We can also
remove more if we want to depending on
the grid size. In this case, the grid
size is just going to determine the
actual bin from which we're removing.
So, as you can see, we have set it to 39
and up until bin 39, it's going to be
removed. Let's set it up a little bit
higher to
53. Actually, we're in here and it
removes it up until 53. We can do the
same with all of the face information.
So, again, let's set this up a little
bit higher so that we can see that we
can reset these. go into all here low
phases and it's just going to remove it
up until 64. And you may feel like you
don't have enough control over it since
the majority of the harmonics you cannot
really touch. But to be honest, you
rarely go above anything that is
happening over here. Most of the energy
of the sound is going to be in here.
Again, a normal saw wave looks like
this. And that means that this stuff
over here is probably as much energy
than all of the harmonics from this
point on forward. meaning that you don't
really have to worry about this stuff of
not being able to edit these harmonics
through some of these processes over
here. The next processes that we can do
is we can resize the tables to be half.
What is going to happen is it is going
to take the table and it's going to
split it up into two wave tables. So as
you can see this splits it up into two
and that is going to happen for all of
the other ones as well. This can mean
that you can lose some tables because
there is a certain limit to it which is
[Music]
almost reached. Now it's reached 256
here. But anyway, we can also do the
opposite process and that is halfing
them. So now we're back to the original.
And of course, you can also go in here
and do that again. So that you can get
these really cool like double shapes
where you're combining say two different
shapes. So if I go in here and I draw
for
example something
like this, what we can do is we can
combine these two into one and you get
this one more complex shape out of that.
The next process allows you to create a
pulse with modulation. So what is going
to happen is it's going to take the
table that you have selected and then
you're able to create a pulse with
modulation from that. So as you can see
what happens is it just generally like
scoots over over time and then towards
the end here as you can see it is
completely moved towards the end here.
So in essence over the course of the
entire wave table this central point is
going to move all the way over here and
in general that results into just a cool
sound. The next process is this notch
all faces for fundamental to 50%. The
manual states preserve the phase of the
lowest frequency fundamental across
various waveforms. But honestly, I don't
know what that means. And to me, it just
does this, which doesn't really tell me
much. It just randomly like morphs the
faces a little bit. Anyway, the next
process, I do know what that does. What
you can do is you can set the spectrum
information of this frame to all of the
other frames. So, this frame, this
spectral information over here is then
going to be distributed across all of
the other frames. Here we can do the
same with the phases here. And what we
can also do is we can involve another
oscillator. So let's just take an
oscillator. I'm going to go to a random
one of my wave tables. If you want to
check out my wave table back, this is
the time to do so. And I'm just going to
set a random position
here. And I'll set spectra from other
oscillator. It's going to give me the
spectral information from the other
oscillator. This oscillator B here.
Actually in this case the way that it
works is very interesting in that what
it does is it doesn't actually take it
from the position as I thought. What it
will do is it will actually match the
table numbers. So the spectral
information from this one over here and
this one over here is going to
match. Here we are at one. Here we are
at one. So if I go between these, you
can see that these match, but we have
different phase information. So that
means that you're able to imprint the
phase information of one wavetable into
the spectra of another wavetable. You
can also do vice versa. If we go in
here, set phases from audio oscillator
so we can get the phase information as
well. And then what we can do, I'm again
going to open up a different wave table.
Let's just go with a different BP sweep
here. And what I'm going to do is I'm
going to go into this one and I would
like to subtract the other spectra from
this oscillator. In this frame, it
didn't do anything, but let's see if
there's other frames where maybe it had
an action. What is essentially going to
happen is that Yeah. So this one is not
going to be in the same area. So let's
just do it the other way around. I'm
going to here generate saw wave. We can
quickly distribute that over the entire
wave cycle or the entire wave table
sorry by again using this set spectra
this frame to all here. And then we can
go in here and then subtract the other
oscillator. As you can see the other
oscillator has been subtracted from the
saw wave over here. And that is going to
happen for every single frame. So this
is basically an easy way to create these
cool inverse wavetables. And this is
also the way that you can create random
gap series. So what you would want to do
for that is you can go into the other
wave table over here and I'm going to
create first of all what I'm going to do
is I'm going to clear all of the phases
here and then go generate saw wave
random gaps here. I'm going to go in
here and set all of the wave tables to
be equal by just using set spectra and
then set faces. So all of the wave
cycles are going to be the exact same.
And now we can subtract all of this
information from this wave table over
here from these wave cycles. And we just
do that a couple of times. So subtract
maybe sometimes once is enough but
sometimes you have to do it a few times.
So now we have this wave table with the
original spectral balance still intact
but with the gaps in there. So that is a
cool way to create these almost like
tonally strange wave tables because
they're just like missing harmonics in
interesting ways. Anyway, the next
process allows you to blur things. So
the way that that's going to work is let
me just draw something a little bit more
complex. And then I'm going to set this
to say 14 here. Again, this is
controllable by the grid size, and it
allows us to blur it, meaning that it's
going to smoon out all of the spectra
for us. We can do the same thing with
all of the faces. So, it's going to blur
all of the phases. I don't know why in
this way, it is still like slightly uns
smooth here, but that should be okay.
Either way, the way that it's supposed
to work is that it treats them as groups
and smooth them out over this axis over
here. What we can also do is smoothen
out over the wavetable axis over this
axis basically. So this would be like
the Z direction almost and that is done
with this adjacent frames here. Again
this allows you to therefore smoothen
between different frames making the
transition smoother between them. And
then finally the final process is this
shift horizontal to zero crossing which
we've seen before but this time it's
going to be for all wave cycles. Now,
let's say that I want to take a bunch of
wave cycles, say from over here to over
here, and I want to delete them. You can
just do that with the delete control.
What I would like to be able to do is
smoothly morph between these two wave
cycles here, between these two frames.
What you can do is have multiple
different ways of morphing. And if I
click here, as you can see, the only
thing that updates is the number. That
is because all of the morphing frames
are stored internally and basically
interpreted by the oscillator itself. So
you can see that the oscillator is now
smoothly morphing between the two, but
it's just not visible in here. We can
remove these morph tables if we want to
over here. And then we can try out the
spectral morph. So this is just going to
morph in a different way. And it's going
to be based on the actual like
spectral things kind of moving between
one position and the other and all of
the phases kind of moving between one
position and the other. You can also do
that while zeroing the fundamental
phrase or the fundamental frequency or
doing that with all phases. So that is
just going to set all of the phases to
zero and generally you're going to get
like this kind of almost double impulse
kind of shape. Now, next up, quickly
going to oscillator B to show this, but
we have this area over here where you
can quickly morph between all of the
wave cycles that you want. And then it's
just going to load up whichever one that
you land on. In this case, all of these
wave cycles are actually the same. So,
that's not going to show really nicely.
Let's actually go back into a different
wave table of mine to actually show
that. This is a nice noisy one, but you
can see that now it's updating and we're
actually moving between them. Right next
to that you have basic actions like
copy, paste, removal of different parts
that you want. We can initialize all of
them. We can remove the current frame.
We can remove the multi selection which
we did with delete before. We can do up
until the selection. So everything in
front of the selection, everything after
the selection can be done as well over
here. And then the final ability here is
just to keep like the even numbered ones
or the the ones numbered by this amount
here. So say that I want to remove 1
over 64 here. This is what you end up
with with four of them. Then over here,
you're able to sort all of these wave
cycles. You can see that you're able to
sort them in a bunch of different ways.
You can also randomly sort them and you
can reverse the order here. Then to the
right of that, we have the formula
parser, which means that I have to now
explain you the entire scripting
language that comes with Serum as well.
No, just kidding. I'm not going to do
that, but it is available in the manual.
For now, all that you need to know is
that you can click over here and there's
going to be a whole bunch of different
formulas available that you're going to
be able to choose from and apply to the
wave tables. And as you can see, some of
them just actually generate like a full
wave table or something like that. These
seem pretty wild, but others maybe like
process them in interesting ways.
Doesn't seem like this one does. This
seems to also just be generating a wave
table of some way. I don't know what it
is. I do know that there's these
interesting processes here. Main ones
that you're going to be using is
squareify and squareify alt because it
allows you to remove the odd harmonics
or all of the even harmonics. If I go to
multis and then squareify alt, it's
going to get rid of all of the auto
harmonics here. So that's the wavetable
editor, meaning that it's now time to
move on to the preset browser, which we
can see over here. We start off with all
of our folders, which we can export down
here. We have our serum one presets and
all of my presets that are in there. I
also have all of my user presets, which
I only have made three of them. And then
we have all of the factory presets,
which we can browse through. Down below,
we have these categories or tags.
Categories are like types of sounds. So
drums, bass, uh, ambience, hits,
keyboards, that kind of thing. And tax
are more like properties. So it's maybe
like clipping, it uses a granular, it
uses a multi-sample, it uses a wave
table. As you can see, it's serum
effects, it's serum 1 or serum 2. You
also have ratings here. Currently, I
don't have any rating set, but you can
do that over here. What is really cool
about this preset browser is the
previews.
[Music]
Have a guess how many techno songs
you're going to hear in the next year
with this sound in them and this exact
rhythm. It's going to be the same thing
with like the silent 303 patch. I don't
know if you remember that
[Music]
one. So, this is really cool. This means
that there's actually individual
melodies coming with all of these
presets and these are actually available
in the clip here. This case this is just
an arp. So this is triggering the
[Music]
arp. You can see the actual arp is the
one that is doing it. And here we can
see the pattern. Of course you come with
different patterns as well.
[Music]
[Applause]
now. As you can guess, this is just your
normal preset browser. So, you can just
scroll through it as well and just find
the preset that you want. If you know
exactly which preset that you want, you
can always search for it here. If I know
that I want to find a certain bass and I
know that it ends with bass,
I have now found my tall base. If you
want to order presets, you can do that
over here. There's also some other
options. Main one of interest is the
hybrid dice here. Also, the load random
preset. Randomly choosing a preset can
be a nice boost of inspiration. But this
hybrid dice here is very very
interesting because it's going to take
some of the presets in your selection in
your list here. Could be in any
selection, any search that you have or
any certain group that you're in. and
it's just going to create a new presets
from different components of different
presets, meaning that it's probably
going to sound good. So, what we have
created here is going to be all of these
presets
[Music]
combined and it does indeed sound very
very cool. There's a few more options
over here which are interesting. you can
auto play the previews, meaning that if
you just click on
[Music]
it, we also have a default clip. So, if
there's no preview available because
there's nothing loaded in here, then
it's just going to use a default clip.
And then, of course, you can select
which one of the three it's going to
use. You can also edit these quickly.
Have to see where it is. But I believe
if I go into Serum 2 presets and then
into clips, you're going to see yes,
default one, default 2, default 3. So
you can replace these with your own MIDI
clips if you want to. I do believe they
have to have the same name in order for
them to show up over here. But if you
don't like the original melodies, you
can have it play a melody of your own.
Finally, at the right here, we have some
extra information about the presets.
Main thing that you're going to find
that you cannot find anywhere else is
going to be notes. And then also the
text with which the preset is tagged.
The next thing that I want to talk about
is some bloatware because Serum 2 when
you install it on your PC, it actually
comes with a secondary plugin. And this
is really annoying. You have to go in
there and delete it. No, just kidding.
It's actually really useful because it
is called Serum Effects. I have it over
here in my little handy menu. And as you
can see, this is just an instance of
Serum that loads up in the effects
stage. And what is going to happen is
that you're going to have an input and
an output. That is why we have two
monitorings over here. and everything in
the effects chain is just going to be
processed. And that means that you can
use Serum's effects on other sins as
well. What you can also do is hop into
the oscillator tab, turn on the noise
here, and this is also an audio input,
meaning that you can use the oscillators
in here, the filter in here, and all of
the other things in here as well. Of
course, this thing also just receives
MIDI if you just want to use this as a
syn as well. Do keep in mind that
there's this extra node latch option
over here which makes it so that LFOs
and any other time based effects
actually sync to the DAW otherwise LFOs
won't work. But then you can basically
use this as an instance of Serum and
either send it audio or send it MIDI and
then just do with it whatever you want
and it's just going to load up as an
effect. Now the next thing that I want
to talk about is that there's many more
things that I could talk about. For
example, you can drag images into it so
that it converts the image into a wave
table. If you go into the modulation
over here and you set up a modulation
with for example the envelope on the
pitch here, what I can go and do is I
can type in 12 semmitones to get exactly
an octave of modulation amount. And in
the wave table editor, instead of
entering a formula, what I can also do
is I can just add it to quotes and just
type any
text and it's going to convert that into
text to speech. It's not going to sound
very good as text to pitch, but it is a
very interesting sound design
[Music]
tool. Can really almost hear
[Applause]
it. Let's just set a modulation through
it. That's going to be much easier.
probably not going to use this for
actual speech. I'm mainly going to use
this for very interesting sound design
stuff. What I also forgot to mention is
probably around a dozen different like
right click options. Uh you can
basically right click on any like
parameter and one of the three is going
to have like interesting extra like
smooth interpolation over here. And I
don't know, let's see. It's going to
really depend on the parameter. I know
that there's something in the spectral
one on the scan, which is this phase
lock and transients, which is really
important because it allows you to get
really strong transients out of uh the
spectral engine, which you normally
cannot do. Another thing that I didn't
fully explain is that you have all of
these modulators over here, but we also
saw in the matrix that you can use the
oscillators or the filters as a
modulation source. That means that you
can just drag in a filter or a
oscillator like this and start
modulating stuff. This actually works at
audio rate and it's really impressive
that basically everything modulatable
works at audio rate and sounds like you
would expect at audio rate. Like this is
very mathematical and very technical but
it's actually really hard to implement
that fast of a modulation and actually
have it be represented accurately. But
from everything that I've been able to
tell this since does it very very well.
So I'm really glad that we have it. And
honestly there's just so many more cool
tricks that I can go into. I can show
you endless different patches. I can
show you endless different things. Let's
just do a few more tracks and then we'll
call it for today. Uh first of all, I'm
going to go into the mixer and I'm going
to set
[Music]
up. All right, I think that's enough
serum for today. Uh I've been filming
for now 7 hours, so that is going to be
enough filming for me. I don't know how
long this is going to get once I edit
all of this down. Either way, I hope you
enjoyed this. I definitely enjoyed
learning about the synth and discovering
everything that there is to know, or at
least as much as there is to know about
it. I am sure that there is some more
stuff that I haven't found out. And I'm
also looking forward to making many,
many more videos using Serum 2 where
we're going to be exploring everything
more in a practical sense and we're
going to dive in and do some actual
sound design with it. For now, I just
wanted to give you a full overview of
the synth and what it is actually
capable of, what all of the controls are
doing, so that you can just get on your
way and start sound designing with
it. So, hopefully that is now exactly
what you're going to do and you're going
to go off of YouTube because you have
been watching content for too long now
officially. But, I do want to thank you
for sticking around for this long. I
hope that you enjoyed the video and I
hope to see you in the next one.
Bye-bye.